<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians dayly practice; or, A practical discourse of prayer. By Sampson Tounesend, minister of Gods word at Hackford in Whitwell in Norffolke. Imprimatur Edm. Calamy.</title>
            <author>Townsend, Sampson.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94771</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1803_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209927</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868773</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868773</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170392</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94771)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170392)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 225:E1803[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians dayly practice; or, A practical discourse of prayer. By Sampson Tounesend, minister of Gods word at Hackford in Whitwell in Norffolke. Imprimatur Edm. Calamy.</title>
                  <author>Townsend, Sampson.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.M. for George Calvert, at the signe of the Half-Moon in St. Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "nouemb: 1659".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS DAYLY PRACTICE; OR, A practical diſcourſe of PRAYER. By <hi>Sampſon Touneſend,</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Hackford</hi> in <hi>Whitwell</hi> in <hi>Norffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Even and morning, and at noon will I pray, and cry aloud, and he ſhall hear my voice</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 55.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur EDM. CALAMY.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>George Calvert,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL his very much honoured Friend <hi>BARNARD CHURCH,</hi> Eſq. Alderman and Magiſtrate of the Famous City of <hi>NORWICH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had Preacht ſeveral Sermons upon the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Prayer (I bleſſe God) they were not without ſome profit;
<pb facs="tcp:170392:3"/>For I was earneſtly deſired, by a Religious Gentleman of my Pariſh, to give him the Heads thereof in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for he told me he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended them a ſufficient Rule to direct him in the whole courſe of his life, as touching that Duty, and reſolved to make uſe of them for that purpoſe. And when in order to the ſatisfying of his deſires, I had drawn out the Heads of thoſe Sermons, I thought with my ſelf, if they were repreſented to publick view, they might take the ſame effect upon ſome
<pb facs="tcp:170392:3"/>other hearts in the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they did upon his in Hearing, and (I bleſſe God in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) upon my own in the Preaching. And Gods glory in the good of his Church being the main end I aimed at in being Ordained unto, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering upon the work of the Miniſtery: hoping this end may be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as by my Preaching, ſo by my Writing, I have ventured upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of this Treatiſe of Prayer; and although many Learned Pens have
<pb facs="tcp:170392:4"/>publiſhed ſeveral Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on this ſubject; and therefore it may be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a bold preſumption in me to expreſſe my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in writing. (For both my preaching and writing, may poſſibly be eſteemed by ſome as fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe (at leaſt) in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thoſe, whoſe Learning, and Eloquence of ſtyle is (many times) beyond the reach of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary capacities to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them:) Yet am I not in the leaſt diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged therefrom, ſeeing it pleaſeth God, by ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:170392:4"/>preaching as the world counts Fooliſhneſſe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.21.</note> to ſave them that beleeve. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving upon the former grounds adventured to write: I have made bold to Dedicate theſe firſt fruits of my labours (in this kind) to your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; That hereby I might expreſſe my thankfulneſſe for the many favours I have received from you from time to time. And although you cannot but diſcerne my weakneſſe in the managing of ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a ſubject, yet ſuch is your goodneſſe, as you
<pb facs="tcp:170392:5"/>will not ſlight it, becauſe Prayer is the duty you deerly love, and daily practice: And you cannot but like any work (though but meanly managed) that may conduce to the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning up of thoſe to the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that are not yet brought into love with it. Sir, I doubt not of your love, notwithſtanding this bold adventure; for your Piety, Humility, and holy Zeal mixed with Chriſtian mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, is ſuch, as cauſeth you to love and reſpect all that love God, and reſpect his glory. But it is not my
<pb facs="tcp:170392:5"/>deſigne to enter upon that labyrinth of publiſhing to the world your Vertues: Only this I may aſſert con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning you, (I hope with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt offence, or ſuſpicion of flattery) That your Chriſtian carriage is ſuch, as it bindeth all that love God, and know you, to love and honour you, for the Vertues that ſhine ſo in you before the ſonnes of men,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> as that the ſons of God are moved (according to divine precept) to glorifie God for you,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.12.</note> and to deſire to Imitate you. And it is no wonder that your life is ſo
<pb facs="tcp:170392:6"/>exemplary; for he that prayeth well, cannot chuſe but live well: He that dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improves grace, by ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily ſupplies of grace, ſhall have <hi>grace for grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1.13</note> or grace upon grace, one grace after another, a daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace, until he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive in glory.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech you, let me have a ſhare in your Prayers to God for me:<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> That I may approve my ſelf to God a workman that needeth not to be aſhamed, rightly dividing the word of truth; That I may ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil my Miniſtery,<note place="margin">Col. 4.17.</note> that I have
<pb facs="tcp:170392:6"/>received in the Lord: That I may ſo live and teach, as that I may both ſave my ſelf, and them that hear me.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.16.</note> Which is the continual prayer, deſire, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of him, that doth not ceaſe to pray for you, and who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble ſervant in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Sampſon Touneſend.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>July</hi> 1. 1658.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:7"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Treatiſe preſented thee with the epitomy of ſeveral Sermons of the duty of Prayer. If thou art one that loves God, thou canſt not but love the Duty:
<pb facs="tcp:170392:8"/>If thou loveſt not God, nor the Duty, thy caſe is ſad, and much to be lamented. For if thou doſt not call upon God, thou canſt not live to the glory of God; but haſt a certain brand upon thee of one that doth no good, but is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given over to all manner of ſinne.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> And if thou art one that doeſt but ſeldom perform the Duty, and takeſt no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it; let me tell thee, although thou makeſt a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Religion, yet thy heart is not right with God, thou art an Hypocrite: For ſo ſaith <hi>Job</hi> of ſuch a one,<note place="margin">Iob 27.10</note> 
               <hi>Will he delight himſelf in the
<pb facs="tcp:170392:8"/>Almighty, will he alwayes call upon God?</hi> No, he will neither delight in God, nor be conſtant in calling upon God. Now that thou maiſt not be prophane, and pray not at all; or Hypocritical, and pray but ſeldom, and by fits; but that thou maiſt be quickned up, to the faithful and frequent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this ſo neceſſary a Duty, I have written this following Treatiſe. And for a further light in, and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the Duty, I ſhall in this Epiſtle, ſhew you,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Several definitions of the Duty, given by ſeveral Holy men.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:9"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> I ſhall ſhew you ſome Examples of the conſtant and frequent practice of the Duty.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſhall ſhew you the excellent, and great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges that belong to Gods people, that are frequent and conſtant in this duty of Prayer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions of Prayer: I find many, I ſhall name ſome. It is a Religious calling upon the name of God, by ſuite or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, in which we deſire all things neceſſary.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>B.</hi> Uſher.</note> It is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious preſenting of our wills before God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Amos.</note> It is a lifting up of the mind to God.<note place="margin">Muſculus.</note> It is an ardent, and earneſt laying
<pb facs="tcp:170392:9"/>open of our heart before God, whereby from Faith in Chriſt, we do either requeſt, or entreat for any thing, or do give thanks for benefits received, whereby is gathered, that the Ten Commandements, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſalutation, and the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Creed, are no Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, becauſe in thoſe nothing is asked of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bucanus</hi> common places. <hi>Leighs</hi> body of Divin. <hi>Robinſons</hi> Reſolves.</note> though ſimple people uſe thoſe as Prayers. It is an humble diſcourſe of the ſoul with God. It is a conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with God, by which Gods love to us, and our love to God is encreaſed. It is an humble, hearty, and holy requeſt made according to Gods will, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb facs="tcp:170392:10"/>up by Faith to God in the Name of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Elton</hi> on the Lords prayer.</note> for things needful for the body or ſoul. It is a putting up of our requeſts to God according to his word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> on the Lords prayer.</note> from a contrite heart, in the Name of Chriſt, with aſſurance to be heard. It is the breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit of God,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6. Rom. 8.14 28.</note> and a proper action of the ſonnes of God. You ſee what the duty is; It is a work of Gods Spirit: Therefore beg the Spirit that thou maiſt pray:<note place="margin">Pſ. 51.12. Luk. 11.13</note> It is a free Spirit, becauſe it is freely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to thoſe that ask it.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> And it ſo helpeth us in the duty of Prayer, that it makes us (which before we ſtreightned)
<pb facs="tcp:170392:10"/>to be free in the work.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>For where the ſpirit of the Lord is, there is liberty.</hi> And from hence it is that Gods Children are ſo frequent in the Duty: which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing I propounded to ſpeak too. Believe it, God hath never a Child but it is ever craving; They pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.17.</note> becauſe they find con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual need of Gods grace and help, and they find continual ſupplies thereof as an anſwer of Prayers. I read, That <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great made his Court a Church where Prayers were made. <hi>Jerom</hi> lived four years with Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb facs="tcp:170392:11"/>Faſtings, and Prayers. <hi>Bernard</hi> prayed day and night till his knees were ſo weary with faſting and prayer, that they could not uphold his body. <hi>Latimer</hi> (many times) continued ſo long in fervent Prayer, that he was not able to get up without help. And I read, that <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus</hi> prayed thrice a day. <hi>Luther</hi> let no day paſſe over his head in which he ſpent not three hours at leaſt in Prayer. Maſter <hi>Robert Bolton</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conſtantly ſix times a day, twice with his Family, twice with his Wife, and twice in ſecret. Maſter <hi>John Bruen</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170392:11"/>prayed ſeven times a day. And why are Gods ſervants thus frequent in prayer? Surely it is becauſe they find no trade that hath ſo quick and gainful returnes as this, and therefore they follow it ſo hard. And this leads me to the third and laſt thing I propounded to ſpeak to; and that is the excellent and great priviledges that belong to Gods people, that are frequent and conſtant in this Duty O! praying Chriſtian, how great are thy priviledges? Although thou maieſt be ſlighted, and diſ-eſteemed by man, yet thou hast free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb facs="tcp:170392:12"/>to conferre with the King of Heaven;<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> who not onely delights to hear thy voice, but inviteth thee to come unto him, and promiſeth to give thee whatſoever thou askeſt of him.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.7.</note> As long as thou conſtantly acquainteſt thy ſelf with God by prayer, thou ſhalt be ſure to have him thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant friend,<note place="margin">Job. 22.21 24.</note> who will never fail,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> nor forſake thee, but will abundantly ſupply unto thee, the want of all unfaithful, and unconſtant friends that deſert thee: where prayer is not wanting, grace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort cannot be wanting.<note place="margin">John 16.23.24.</note> Thou that art a child of God, and
<pb facs="tcp:170392:12"/>doſt the will of God, let the deſires of thy heart to God in Prayer be never ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, God will ſatisfie all thy deſires.<note place="margin">Joh. 15.7. Pſal. 37.4.</note> And it muſt needs be thus, for that God, <hi>that is able to do</hi> (for his children, and many times <hi>doth for them</hi>) <hi>exceedingly above all that they ask or think,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 3.20.</note> He will not, (and for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſake) he cannot deny any of thoſe needful things his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ask of him.<note place="margin">Pſ. 81.10.</note> By prayer Gods people, not only obtain all the good things they pray for,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.5</note> but alſo a ſanctified uſe of all thoſe good things. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is given by God to
<pb facs="tcp:170392:13"/>man in a way of mercy, is given him as an anſwer of his Prayers.<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.14, 15.</note> Prayer is the key that open all the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of God.<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.33, 35.</note> It is the great inſtrument of removing all evils from the ſoul and the body. It is the Character of the Saints. It is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Gods promiſes;<note place="margin">Ezek. 36, 37.</note> the forerunner of Gods perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances.<note place="margin">Jer. 31.9.</note> The happy privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the praying Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an are beyond expreſsion. They have a conſtant Communion with God. They have dayly ſupplies of grace from God,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.3</note> whereby they are enabled to ſerve and pleaſe God, while
<pb facs="tcp:170392:13"/>they live here;<note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> and they ſhall be made everlaſtingly happy with God hereafter.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.13.</note> No grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter priviledges can be obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then theſe; yet theſe are the priviledges of the praying Chriſtian. Would you be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py? pray, pray that your joy may be full:<note place="margin">John 16.24.</note> He deſerves to be miſerable, that might be made happy by praying, and yet will not ſet upon the Duty. But I ſhall pray, and hope, that theſe my labours may be ſuccesful for the ends inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; in directing in, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing to the Duty, thoſe that have not uſed it: in comforting and encouraging thoſe in the
<pb facs="tcp:170392:14"/>Duty, that dayly practiſe it. And in whomſoever either of theſe ends be promoted, let God have the glory; and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not to pray for him, who is, to his power,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in all Chriſtian ſervices for thy ſouls good,</hi> Sampſon Touneſend.</signed>
               <date>July <hi>1. 1658.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:14"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>DOct.</hi> It is the duty of the people of God to pray. <hi>pag. 3</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> What prayer is. It is</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> A work of Gods Spirit. <hi>pag. 4</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> It floweth out of the ſpirit and heart of man: or, it is a talking of the heart and ſoul with God. <hi>pag. 5</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The ſeveral kinds of prayer</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170392:15"/>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Are </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Mental. <hi>pag. 6</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Vocal.</item>
                           <item>Publick, Private.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> The preparations to prayer, </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Are</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Prayer.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Meditation. <hi>pag. 8 </hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Meditate upon</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>1.</hi> Gods infinite greatneſse.</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>2.</hi> The promiſes.</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>3.</hi> Thine own wants and vileneſs. <hi>pag. 9</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> The duties or graces requiſite in prayer: are,</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Knowledge. <hi>pag. 9</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Faith.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Humility. <hi>pag. 10</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Purity of heart.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Love to our brethren.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Zeal and fervency. <hi>pag. 11</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> Unwearied conſtancy.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> We muſt pray in the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>pag. 12</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> In the name and mediation of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>pag. 13</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10.</hi> For things agreeable to Gods will.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>11.</hi> We muſt uſe a due order in prayer. <hi>pag. 14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>12.</hi> Take heed of loving long prayers. <hi>pag. 15</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Laſtly, hate the ſin you pray againſt, and love
<pb facs="tcp:170392:15"/>the grace you pray for. <hi>pag. 16</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> The geſtures in prayer are,</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Kneeling. <hi>pag. 18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Lifting and ſpreading forth the hands. <hi>pag. 20.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Lifting up of the eyes. <hi>pag. 22</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> For men to be uncovered. <hi>pag. 23</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>In what caſe geſtures may be omitted. <hi>pag. 25</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Reprehenſion for theſe that neglect the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, or uſe contrary geſtures. <hi>pag. 29</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Exhortation, to uſe more reverence in prayer. <hi>pag. 31</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Six ſeveral motives to the duty of prayer.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Firſt ſort of motives are taken from the neceſsity of the duty.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> God commands it. <hi>pag. 33</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> The creature is ſanctifyed by it.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> There is no comfort in the Ordinances with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. <hi>pag. 34</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> We lie under Gods curſe if we neglect it.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A</hi> ſecond ſort of motives, are taken from the benefits that come by prayer.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> It ſhall not be in vain. <hi>pag. 35</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> It is a ſigne of true Converſion.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> It is alwayes accompanied with ſalvation.</item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:170392:16"/>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> It is ſweet and pleaſant in Gods ears. <hi>pag. 36</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> It will give eaſe to the grieved heart.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6.</hi> It is the only means to get the heart filled with ſpiritual graces.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>7.</hi> By prayer we approach into Gods preſence. <hi>pag. 37</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A</hi> third ſort of motives, are taken from the power and goodneſſe of God.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> God hath ſtiled himſelf a God hearing prayer.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> He is able to help his people. <hi>pag. 38</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> He is willing to help them.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> He hath made many promiſes to help them. <hi>pag. 39</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Seventhly: the times of prayer, in general, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually. <hi>pag. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>That is </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Upon all opportunites.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Without fainting. <hi>pag. 41</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> Daily, all their life long.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>The ſpecial times of prayer: are,</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>The Lords dayes, faſting dayes, thanksgiving dayes, and upon private occaſions. <hi>pag. 42</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>But more particularly,</item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> Every day. <hi>pag. 43</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:170392:16"/>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>2.</hi> Twice every day: morning and evening. <hi>pag. 44</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reaſons why we muſt be thus conſtant and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in prayer, are becauſe,</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> We continually need bleſsings. <hi>pag. 45</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Without prayer our calling proſpers not. <hi>pag. 46</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> Without it, our graces will decay.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> The Devils temptations will prevail. <hi>pag. 47</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> Our ſins will multiply, and, <hi>pag. 48</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6.</hi> We have need to beg daily pardon of ſin. <hi>pag. 49</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Eightly and laſtly: ſeveral objections againſt prayer, are anſwered, as,</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1. Object.</hi> It is to no purpoſe to pray.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe God knoweth our wants</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> He hath decreed what ſhall befall every man.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> He is ready to give what is fit for us.</item>
                           <item>This is anſwered. <hi>pag. 50</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2. Object.</hi> It is needleſſe becauſe the good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of things depend upons ſecond cauſes, and natural means.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>This is anſwered. <hi>pag. 54</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3. Object.</hi> They that never pray, do as well as they that pray moſt: what need then is there of this conſtant praying?</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:17"/>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>This is anſwered. <hi>pag. 56</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4. Object.</hi> I am unable to pray, I would pray, but I want faith, and the ſpirit of prayer.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>This is anſwered. <hi>pag. 59</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5. Object.</hi> I would fain pray, but I am ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and unworthy a wretch I dare not: <hi>I know God heareth not ſinners,</hi> John <hi>9.31.</hi> Yet ſuch a one am I, and therefore I dare not pray</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>This is anſwered. <hi>pag. 16</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6. Object.</hi> I have prayed, but I can find no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>This is anſwered <hi>pag. 66</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7. Object.</hi> I can finde no good by praying, but I finde I am rather the worſe.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>This is anſwered. <hi>pag. 71</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div type="list_of_uses">
               <pb facs="tcp:170392:17"/>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The uſe of all: is,</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> For Inſtruction.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> For Reprehenſion.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> For Conſolation.</item>
                     <item>Laſtly, for Exhortation.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>1 Uſe.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> It inſtructs us in the right manner of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: where, <hi>pag. 75</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> We ſee, dead, dull, formal, heartleſſe prayers are not pleaſing to God.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> That wicked men that have not the Spirit of God, cannot pleaſe God in their praying. <hi>pag. 76</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> It inſtructs us concerning the power of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: of which many examples in Scripture are inſtanced. <hi>pag. 77</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>2. Uſe.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Reprehenſion, divers are reproved.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Thoſe that pray not at all <hi>pag. 81</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Thoſe that are laſie and ſluggiſh in prayer. <hi>pag. 82</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Thoſe that have evil ends in praying. <hi>pag. 83</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Thoſe that pray for light and ſlight things.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Thoſe that are formal and hypocritical in their prayers.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Thoſe that pray without judgment or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. <hi>pag. 84</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:18"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> Thoſe that pray, but reſolve to go on in their ſinnes. <hi>pag. 88</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Laſtly, Thoſe that pray without faith and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency. <hi>pag. 90</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>3. Uſe.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Conſolation: for all thoſe that are faithful, frequent, conſtant and fervent in this duty of prayer.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> God uſually bleſſeth thoſe families where prayers are daily uſed. <hi>pag. 91</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> God will anſwer ſecret prayers.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> If thou canſt pray in faith, it is a certain ſigne thou haſt the truth of grace; thou art a childe of God, and ſhall be ſaved. <hi>pag. 92</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> If thy heart be ſincere in prayer, God will accept of thee, although thou haſt many fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. <hi>pag. 93</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> When words fail, tears, ſighs, and groanes, are a ſigne thou haſt the ſpirit of prayer. <hi>pag. 94</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:20"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Sincere ſeeking of God, will give comfort in all afflictions and trials. <hi>pag. 95</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7. A</hi> conſtant courſe of praying, is a certain ſigne, the ſinne or judgement thou prayeſt againſt ſhall be removed, or the mercy thou prayeſt for, ſhall be granted. <hi>pag. 96</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> That God that calleth thee to pray, he is able, ready and willing to help thee. <hi>pag. 98</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Laſtly, all the prayers of Gods faithful ſervants on earth, ſhall undoubtedly be heard, and anſwered in heaven. If,</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> They be Righteous perſons, and, <hi>pag. 99</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Ask in the Name of Chriſt. <hi>pag. 100</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> According to the will of God.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The fourth and laſt uſe is,</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>Exhortation: to the performance of the duty of prayer: where, firſt you have
<pb facs="tcp:170392:21"/>divers Directions in the duty: as,</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Labour to be reconciled to Chriſt. <hi>pag. 102</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Ask nothing but what God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give. <hi>pag. 103</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Seek God with a contrite and broken heart. <hi>pag. 104</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Take heed of wandering thoughts in prayer.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Beare in thy minde all the ſinnes thou art to pray againſt, and the graces thou art to pray for: mind alſo the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies thou haſt received, to be thankful for them. <hi>pag. 105</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> In thy prayers have a high eſteem of God. <hi>pag. 106</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> Be as ready to be thankful for what you have received, as to ſeek God for what you want.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> When your prayers be ended, take heed you reſt not in the duty. <hi>pag. 107</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> Let Gods glory be your utmoſt aime in all your prayers. <hi>pag. 108</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:21"/>
                     <item>Laſtly, Take heede of a ſelfiſh ſpirit prayer: Pray for all men. <hi>pag. 109</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Two queſtions concerning prayer anſwered.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1. Queſtion.</hi> I cannot tell how to pray, I want utterance: whether or no, is not my reading a forme of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er acceptable with God in this caſe?</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>This is anſwered. <hi>pag. 110.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2. Queſtion.</hi> I cannot read, and I know not how to pray: what ſhall I do in this caſe?</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>This is anſwered. <hi>pag. 113</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Laſtly, four encouragementts to the duty of prayer.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> God is ſo well pleaſed with it, That he hath heard the prayers of men for temporal things, that had no grace. <hi>pag. 117</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Whoſoever ſets upon the duty with a ſincere
<pb facs="tcp:170392:22"/>heart, ſhall find God carrying of him on in it beyond expectation. <hi>pag. 118</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> God is more ready to anſwer his people than they are to ask. <hi>pag. 120</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Laſtly, God is ſo well pleaſed with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as that he makes his readineſſe to hear a ground of encouragement to quicken them to the duty. <hi>pag. 121</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Printed by <hi>George Calvert</hi> at the ſigne of the Half-Moon in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MYſteriorum &amp; Medulla Bibliorum.</hi> The Myſtery and Marrow of the Bible: <hi>viz.</hi> Gods Covenants <hi>with man,</hi> in the <hi>Firſt Adam,</hi> before the Fall: and in the <hi>Laſt Adam Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> after the Fall; From the beginning to the end of the World; by <hi>Francis Roberts,</hi> M. A. in fol.</p>
            <p>The Communicant inſtructed, or practical dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for the worthy receiving the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: in octavo.</p>
            <p>The Believers Evidences for eternal life; in octa.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:19"/>
            <head>An Alphabetical Table of the chief things handled in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <label>A</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Ability to pray ſhall not be wanting to him that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on in the duty. <hi>pag. 118</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Anguiſh of mind, the cauſe why Gods people regard not anſwer of prayers. <hi>pag. 73</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Anſwer of prayers, five wayes. <hi>pag. 66</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Anſwer of prayers, ſometimes as a judgment. <hi>pag. 70</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Aſa's ſin in ſeeking to the Phyſitian, and not to God. <hi>pag. 54</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ask in the name of Chriſt according to the will of God, and thou ſhalt be anſwered. <hi>pag. 100</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What it is to <hi>ask</hi> in the Name of Chriſt. <hi>pag. 13</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>No warrant to <hi>ask</hi> what God hath not promiſed to give. <hi>pag. 103</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>God is more ready to <hi>anſwer</hi> than we are to <hi>ask. pag. 120</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>B</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Better with him that prayeth, than with him that prayeth not. <hi>pag. 56</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Benefits that come by prayer. <hi>pag. 35</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Bleſſings of God, not to be expected without prayer. <hi>pag. 46</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:20"/>
                     <item>Bodies as well as ſouls muſt worſhip God. <hi>pag. 19</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>C</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Call of God to prayer, a ſign God intends to anſwer. <hi>pag. 98</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A Catalogue of ſins, of graces, and of bleſſings, will furniſh thee with matter of prayer. <hi>pag. 105</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cautions in reading forms of prayer. <hi>pag. 112</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Commandments no prayers. <hi>pag. 85</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Conſtant ſeeking God, a certain ſign God will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>pag. 96</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Continual praying, what is meant by it. <hi>pag. 40</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Creed, no prayer. <hi>pag. 87</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>D</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Daily prayers, a means to obtain grace, and to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere and increaſe therein. <hi>pag. 46</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Dead, dull, formal, heartleſſe prayers, are not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto God. <hi>pag. 75</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Delayes of God are no denials. <hi>pag. 72</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Directions in the duty of prayer. <hi>pag. 102</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The <hi>Divel</hi> is conquered, and daily ſins prevented by daily prayers. <hi>pag. 47, 48</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Doubting in prayer ſinful. <hi>pag. 90</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>E</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Earthly things muſt be ſought conditionally. <hi>pag. 14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Ends bad in prayer ſpoil the duty. <hi>pag. 83</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Eſteem highly of God in prayer. <hi>pag. 106</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Examples of frequent prayer. See Epiſt. to read.</item>
                     <item>Examples of five in Scripture, that went to God in the ſenſe of ſin, and obtained mercy. <hi>pag. 64</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:18"/>
                     <item>Eyes lift up to God in prayer, examples for it. <hi>pag. 22</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>F</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Faith the condition upon which the promiſe of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of prayers is made. <hi>pag. 90</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faith may be, when thou feeleſt it not. <hi>pag. 59</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faithful praying, is a ſign of one that hath grace, that is a child of God, and ſhall be ſaved. <hi>pag. 92</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Family prayers bring a bleſſing upon the family. <hi>pag. 91</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Forms of prayer lawful. <hi>pag. 110</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>G</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Geſtures in prayer. <hi>pag. 18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>God muſt firſt ſpeak to the heart, before the heart can ſpeak to God. <hi>pag. 5</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>God muſt be ſought in the uſe of means. <hi>pag. 54</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gods goodneſſe, a motive to prayer. <hi>pag. 37</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gods ready hearing others, an encouragement to prayer. <hi>pag. 121</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gods time, the best time for anſwering prayers. <hi>pag. 100</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gods glory only to be ſought in prayer. <hi>pag. 108</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Grace in the heart will enable a man to pray with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reading forms. <hi>pag. 113</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>H</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Hands as well as hearts muſt be lifted up to God in prayer. <hi>pag. 20</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hands lift up in prayer, what it ſignifies. <hi>pag. 21</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hate the ſin you pray againſt. <hi>pag. 16</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Heart broken for ſin, ſhall be broken by God from ſin. <hi>pag. 104</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:19"/>
                     <item>Heart to pray: where given, God will lend an ear to hear. <hi>pag. 115</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Heavenly things muſt be ſought abſolutely. <hi>pag. 14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hypocrites ſerve not God, out of the love they bear to him. <hi>pag. 84</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Humility requiſite in prayer. <hi>pag. 10</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>I</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>If thy heart <hi>incline</hi> to ſin, Gods ear will not incline to thy prayers. <hi>pag. 89</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Incouragements four, to the duty of prayer. <hi>pag. 117</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Inſtructions in the right manner of prayer. <hi>pag. 75</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Intereſt in Chriſt makes both our perſons and our prayers accepted. <hi>pag. 102</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>K</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Kneeling a part of divine worſhip. <hi>pag. 18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Kneeling in prayer: examples for it. <hi>pag. 19</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Knowledge requiſite in prayer. <hi>pag. 9</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>L</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Labours to no purpoſe without Gods bleſſing. <hi>pag. 55</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A laſie poſture in prayer is not to be uſed. <hi>pag. 28</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Laſie and ſluggiſh prayers provoke God. <hi>pag. 82</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Love to our brethren, requiſite in prayer. <hi>pag. 10</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Love not long prayers. <hi>pag. 15</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Love the grace you pray for. <hi>pag. 17</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>M</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Meditation, a help to prayer. <hi>pag. 8</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Men to be uncovered in prayer. <hi>pag. 23</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mental prayer. <hi>pag. 6</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:23"/>
                     <item>Morning and Evening, the fitteſt times for prayer. <hi>pag. 44</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Motives to prayer. <hi>pag. 33</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>N</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Needs of Gods people, God is able and willing to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. <hi>pag. 38</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Neceſſity of prayer, in four reſpects. <hi>pag. 33</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>O</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Objections against prayer anſwered. <hi>pag. 50</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Order in prayer required. <hi>pag. 14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Outward geſtures, when they may be omitted. <hi>pag. 25</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>P</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Power of prayer, in divers examples. <hi>pag. 77</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayer what it is. <hi>pag. 4</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayer, ſeveral definitions thereof: See the Epiſtle to the Reader.</item>
                     <item>Pray that you may pray. <hi>pag. 7</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayer, ſeveral requiſites in it. <hi>pag. 9,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>To pray for light and ſlight things, a taking Gods Name in vain. <hi>pag. 83</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayers, five ſeveral wayes anſwered. <hi>pag. 66</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayers anſwered as a judgment, and denied as a mercy. <hi>pag. 70</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayer gives comfort in all afflictions. <hi>pag. 95</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayer may be effectual when a man is indiſpoſed to it, and diſtracted in it. <hi>pag. 59</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayer is the Bucket by which we draw water out of the Wells of ſalvation. <hi>pag. 34</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:24"/>
                     <item>Prayer neglected, expoſes a man to all ſins and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations. <hi>pag. 81, 82</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Pray aright, and be ſure to ſpeed. <hi>pag. 35</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Preparations to prayer. <hi>pag. 7</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Pride keeps men from prayer. <hi>pag. 65</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Priviledges of the praying Chriſtian: ſee the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Reader.</item>
                     <item>Promiſes to prayer. <hi>pag. 39</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>He that turns the <hi>promiſes</hi> into prayers, ſpeaks to God in his own language. <hi>pag. 103</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>Q</label>
               <item>Queſtions, two concerning prayer anſwered. <hi>pag. 110</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>R</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Reaſons, ſix for daily prayers. <hi>pag. 45</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reproof for thoſe that pray without judgment or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding. <hi>pag. 85</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reproof for thoſe that uſe irreverent gestures in prayer. <hi>pag. 29</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reſt not in the duty of prayer. <hi>pag. 107</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reverence in prayer exhorted to. <hi>pag. 31</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reverence in prayer, an effect of faith. <hi>pag. 27</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>S</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sacrifices under the Old Law, morning and evening figured out the Chriſtians daily prayers. <hi>pag. 44</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secret prayers ſhall be anſwered. <hi>pag. 91</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Senſe of ſin ſhould not keep us from prayer. <hi>pag. 63</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sighs and groans a ſign of the ſpirit of prayer, and accepted with God. <hi>pag. 94</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:22"/>
                     <item>Sincerity in prayer, accepted with God, although there be many failings. <hi>pag. 95</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What <hi>ſinners</hi> God will not hear. <hi>pag. 62</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sitting in prayer, not found in Scripture. <hi>pag. 32</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Not greatneſſe of <hi>ſinne,</hi> but want of faith, keeps men from ſeeking Gods mercy. <hi>pag. 5</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>T</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Tears have a voice in Gods ears. <hi>pag. 60</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Temporal things muſt be prayed for conditionally. <hi>pag. 15</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Temporal things given to them that have no grace. <hi>pag. 117</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Be as ready to be <hi>thankful</hi> to God for what you have received, as to ſeek him for what you want. <hi>pag. 106</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Three ſpecial duties to be daily practiſed by every Chriſtian. <hi>pag. 2</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Times of prayer. <hi>pag. 40</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>U</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Vocal prayer. <hi>pag. 6</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief a greater ſin than all thy other ſins. <hi>pag. 65</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly and wicked men pray not. <hi>pag. 81</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>W</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Wait Gods time for an anſwer of prayer. <hi>pag. 100</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Wandering thoughts muſt be avoided in prayer. <hi>pag. 104</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Wicked men that pray not, may have temporal, but not ſpiritual bleſſings. <hi>pag. 56</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Wicked men, how they have a right to what they do enjoy. <hi>pag. 57</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Wicked men cannot pleaſe God in prayer. <hi>pag. 76</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170392:23"/>
                     <item>Words ſhall not be wanting to him that hath a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere heart to ſeek God. <hi>pag. 115</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>Z</label>
               <item>Zeal and fervency required in prayer. <hi>pag. 11</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <div type="part">
               <head>Faults eſcaped, may be thus corrected.</head>
               <p>PAge 14. line 21. read theſe. p. 17. l. 10. blot out <hi>may.</hi> p. 19. l. 8. after glorifie God, adde, <hi>in your body and in your spirit which are Gods.</hi> p. 25. l. the laſt, bl. out mance. p. 28. l. 20. after deadneſſe, adde, and dulneſſe. p. 36. l. 13. after of, adde <hi>from.</hi> p. 38. l. 15. r. God. p. 65. l. 4. r. from his ſins. p. 78. l. 9. r. him. p. 85. l. 12. bl. out <hi>as.</hi> p. 86. l. 6. after ſay. r. to God. p. 86. l. 15. r. teacheth. p. 91. l. 9. r. and ſecretly. p. 99. l. 3. r. <hi>whatſoever.</hi> p. 114. l. 19. r. aſſiſtance. p. 117. after before me, adde <hi>becauſe he humbleth himſelf before me.</hi> p. 121. r. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Marginal faults correct thus.</head>
               <p>Page 13. line 6. r. John. p. 19. l. 22. r. Acts 9.40. p. 45. l. 2. Heb. 13.5. p. 50. l. 22. Phil. 4.6. p. 55. l. 12. r. 1 Corin. p. 63. l. 18. Mat. 9.12. p. 68. l. 6. r. Heb. 5.7. p. 76. l. r. Pſal. 143.8. p. 101. l. 5. Iſa. 8.17.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:24"/>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170392:25"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS DAYLY PRACTICE; OR, A practical diſcourſe of PRAYER. Very uſeful for every Chriſtian. By <hi>Sampſon Touneſend,</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word, Paſtour of <hi>Hackford</hi> and <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> in <hi>Norffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Evening and morning, and at noon will I pray, and cry aloud, and he ſhall hear my voice,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 55.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur. EDM. CALAMY.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>George Calvert,</hi> at the ſigne of the Half-Moon in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard over againſt the little North-door. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170392:25"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIANS <hi>DAYLY PRACTICE;</hi> Being the ſubſtance of eleven <hi>SERMONS,</hi> preached on 1 THESS. 5.17. <hi>Pray.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving undertaken to ſpeak of Prayer; I have choſen this Text as the ſubject upon which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to build my diſcourſe. The Apoſtle having in the former Chapter ſpoken of the laſt Reſurrection, the coming of Chriſt, and the bleſſed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170392:26"/>of thoſe that die in the Lord after the Reſurrection. In this Chapter he prevents a needleſſe inquiry that ſome might make; as they in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.3. <hi>When ſhall theſe things be?</hi> He tels them it ſhall be ſudden, and unexpected, <hi>verſe</hi> 1, 2, 3. and then he exhorts them to watchfulneſſe, that they may be prepared for it, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8. And from the 13 <hi>verſe</hi> to the 23, he exhorts them to ſeveral duties: In the 23 <hi>verſe</hi> he prays for them: In the 25 <hi>verſe</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires them to pray for him; and ſo concludes his Epiſtle. In the verſe before my Text, in the Text, and in the verſe following, he requires three ſpeciall Duties, that are dayly to be practiſed by every Chriſtian. <hi>Rejoyce evermore, Pray without ceaſing; In everything give thanks.</hi> Teaching us, that our joy ſhould be ſuch as it doe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170392:26"/>not hinder Prayer: and our Prayers ſhould be ſuch as they doe not exclude ſpirituall Joy: and then we ſhall have occaſion at all times in every thing to give thanks. The Text it holds forth to us this Doctrine:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is the duty of the people of God to Pray.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning which, I intend to clear up unto you theſe things:
<list>
                  <item>1. To ſhew you what Prayer is.</item>
                  <item>2. The ſeverall kindes of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>3. The preparations to Prayer.</item>
                  <item>4. The duties in Prayer.</item>
                  <item>5. The geſtures in Prayer.</item>
                  <item>6. The motives and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Prayer.</item>
                  <item>7. The times of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>8. And laſtly, I ſhall anſwer divers Objections about Prayer.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And when I have gone through
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170392:27"/>all theſe, I ſhall make Uſe and Application of all.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the nature of Prayer,<note place="margin">Firſt. Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> what it is. Prayer, it is a work of Gods Spirit, and ſo floweth out of the ſpirit and heart of man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, It is a work of Gods Spirit; and hence it is, that it is called <hi>the ſpirit of grace and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 12.10.</note> And the Spirit is ſaid to help Gods Children in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26, 27.</note> And we are commanded to <hi>pray in the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 20.</note> That is, by the help of the holy Ghoſt. And ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>I will pray with the Spirit.</hi> So you ſee it is a work of Gods Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, It floweth out of the ſpirit and heart of man; ſaith <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 62.8.</note> 
               <hi>Pour out your heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.4.</note> 
               <hi>I will pour out my ſoul in me.</hi> When God poures out upon the Soul the ſpirit of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170392:27"/>Grace and Supplication, then the Soul pours out it ſelf to God. And therefore you may take an other definition of Prayer thus:</p>
            <p>It is a talking of the heart and ſoul with God,<note place="margin">Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and of ſuch a heart as is prepared by God. When the ſtrength and ſtream of the heart and affections are drawn out after God in Prayer: This is the Prayer that God will hear and anſwer. <hi>And ye ſhall ſeek me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer 29.13.</note> 
               <hi>and finde me, when ye ſhall ſearch for me with all your heart.</hi> And none can thus ſeek God with all the heart, till God prepare, and diſpoſe the heart thus to ſeek him.<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.8.</note> 
               <hi>When thou ſayeſt ſeek ye my face, my heart ſaid unto thee, thy face Lord will I ſeek.</hi> God muſt firſt ſpeak to the heart, before the heart can ſpeak ſo to God as he will hear.<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.17</note> 
               <hi>Thou wilt prepare their heart, thou wilt cauſe thine ear to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170392:28"/>hear.</hi> So much for the firſt thing propounded.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> I ſhall ſhew you the ſeverall kindes of Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, There is mental prayer, or the prayer of the minde. And thus <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſaid to cry unto God,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.15.</note> although he uttered no voice. And thus <hi>Hannah</hi> prayed: <hi>She ſpake in her heart onely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>her lips moved, but her voice was not heard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, There is vocal prayer.<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.1.</note> 
               <hi>I cryed unto God with my voice, even unto God with my voice, and he gave ear unto me.</hi> Again, there is ſecret prayer:<note place="margin">Mat. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>When thou prayeſt enter into thy Cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut thy dore, pray to thy Father which is in ſecret, and thy Father which ſeeth in ſecret, ſhall reward thee openly.</hi> And there is publick Prayers with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; and Prayers leſſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170392:28"/>in the Family, or with others. So much for the ſecond thing.</p>
            <p>I come to the third thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded,<note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> The Preparations to Prayer. I ſhall mention onely two:
<list>
                  <item>1. Prayer.</item>
                  <item>2. Meditation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Prayer. Pray that you may pray: Pray that God would direct you how to pray: Thus did <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 141.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Let my prayer be ſet forth before thee as incenſe, and the lifting up of my hands as the evening ſacrifice: Set a watch O Lord, before my mouth, keep the dore of my lips.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, O Lord, do thou ſo order and direct me in my Prayers, that there may not a word proceed out of my mouth, but what is acceptable unto thee. When a man prays dayly that he may pray, by his conſtant cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170392:29"/>of praying, he will be the better fitted for Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A ſecond preparation to prayer is Meditation. Eſpecially meditate on theſe three things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Meditate upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite greatneſſe of the Majeſty of that God to whom thou prayeſt. <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecleſ. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>and let not thine heart be haſty to utter any thing before God; For God is in Heaven, and thou upon Earth, therefore let thy words be few.</hi> This meditation of Gods great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will make thee humble, as it did <hi>Jacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.9 10.</note> who acknowledged he was not worthy of the leaſt of all the mercies of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Meditate on the Promiſes of God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> 
               <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble, and I will hear thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>Ask, and it ſhall be given you.</hi> With many others of the like nature, this Meditation will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170392:29"/>make thee confident in Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, and laſtly, Meditate on thine own wants and vileneſſe, and acknowledge them to God; ſo did <hi>Ezra.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra. 9.6, 7.</note> This Meditation will make thee fervent in Prayer, and it is the Prayer of the humble faithfull fervent ſoul, that ſhall prevail with God. So much for the third thing propounded.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> I ſhall ſhew you the duties or graces requiſite in Prayer, and there are divers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites in Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. <hi>I will pray with the ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>and I will pray with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding alſo.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, I will underſtand, and know what I pray for.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Faith: It is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition upon which the promiſe of anſwer of Prayers is made. <hi>Let him ask in Faith, nothing waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170392:30"/>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 1.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Let not that man think he ſhall receive any thing of the Lord,</hi> that asks doubtingly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Humility: It is the humble ſoul that ſhall prevail with God in Prayer.<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.17</note> 
               <hi>Lord thou haſt heard the deſire of the humble: He giveth grace to the humble.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 4.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4"> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Fourthly, Purity of heart. <hi>Let us draw neer with a true heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>in full aſſurance of Faith, having our hearts ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience.</hi> He that draws nigh to God with an evil heart, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed conſcience, ſhall never ſpeed in his Prayers.<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.18</note> 
               <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me.</hi> If thy heart incline to ſinne, Gods ear will not incline to thy Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, Love to our brethren, is an other duty required in Prayer. If thou prayeſt for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin, and haſt not ſo much
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170392:30"/>love to thy brother, as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him an injury done to thee; God will not hear thy prayers; nor pardon thy ſinnes: for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of pardon is upon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:<note place="margin">Mat. 6.14, 15,</note> 
               <hi>For if ye forgive men their treſpaſſes, your heavenly Father will alſo forgive you: But if you forgive not men their treſpaſſes, neither will you Father forgive you your trepaſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, Zeal and Fervency is required in Prayer. The colder the ſutour, the greater the ſinner. <hi>The effectuall fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 5.16.</note> Prayer is not effectuall, unleſſe it be fervent, though it proceed from a righteous man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, Unwearied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy; we muſt not give over praying, becauſe we have not preſent anſwers: For this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our Saviour Chriſt mentions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170392:31"/>the Parable of the unjuſt Judge and the Widow:<note place="margin">Luke 18.1, to 9.</note> 
               <hi>That men ought alwayes to pray, and not to faint.</hi> And the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us this leſſon of Conſtancy: She would not give over praying, though ſhe had many repulſes,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.22, to 29. Gen. 32.26.</note> till ſhe had that ſhe prayed for. And <hi>Jacob,</hi> he would not let God goe till he had a bleſſing. All which examples ſhew, we muſt uſe unwearied conſtancy in prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eighthly, We muſt pray in the holy Ghoſt; ſo we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Praying in the holy Ghoſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 20.</note> that is, by the help of the holy Ghoſt. This help is promiſed in Prayer.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> 
               <hi>Likewiſe alſo the ſpirit helpeth our infirmities; for we know not what to pray for as we ought, but the ſpirit it ſelf maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion for us with groanings which cannot be uttered.</hi> Without this help our Prayers will not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170392:31"/>Thoſe are the beſt Prayers, that have moſt of the ſpirit of Gods help in them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninethly, Pray in the name and mediation of Jeſu; Chriſt: ſaith Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 John 14.13, 14. John 16.23.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall ask in my name that will I do. Whatſoever ye ſhal ask the Father in my Name, he wil give it you.</hi> To ask in the name of Chriſt, is to ask relying upon the Promiſes, Merit, and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Chriſt; or to deſire to be heard for the merit, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Chriſts ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Tenthly; Pray for things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeble to Gods will; ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 John 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>This is the confidence that we have in him, that if we ask any thing according to his will, he heareth us.</hi> We can have no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of being heard in that which we doe not know whether or no it be according to Gods will. Chriſt did juſtly deny the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170392:32"/>requeſt of her that askt ſhe knew not what.<note place="margin">Mat. 20.21, 22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Eleventhly, Uſe a due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Prayer. Seek Heavenly things firſt and moſt; ſeek earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things in the ſecond place. Saith Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> 
               <hi>Seek firſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> So we are taught in the Lords Prayer, to ſeek firſt the things that concerne Heaven and Happineſs, before we ſeek Earthly bleſſings, We muſt ſeek Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things abſolutely, but Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things conditionally; becauſe Heavenly things are abſolutely neceſſary for us, as Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Sanctification, &amp;c. theſe things we know are agreeable to the will of God; and therefore we are to pray for thoſe things abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, and not with a condition (if it be thy will.) But now for Temporall things, they are not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170392:32"/>abſolutely neceſſary for us, as health, or freedome from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of unreaſonable men, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance out of this or that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; or to proſper, or increaſe in their eſtate in the world, or the like. For theſe things we muſt pray with condition (if it be the will of God.) Becauſe God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, or denieth theſe things to his children, according as he ſees beſt, or moſt fit for each of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. For want of obſerving theſe things, and ſo uſing a due order in Prayer; many times in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a bleſſing, God makes a breach upon them for ſeeking him diſorderly, as it is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord our God made a breach upon us, for that we ſought him not after the due order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Twelthly, Take heed of loving long Prayers, and think not to be heard becauſe your Prayers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170392:33"/>are long. Saith Chriſt, <hi>When you pray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>uſe not vain repetitions, as the Heathen doe, For they think they ſhall be heard for their much ſpeaking.</hi> Long prayers can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintain their vigour; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly there will be vain repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as you ſee it was with the Heathen. Know that God takes not mens Prayers by tale, but by weight. It is not gifts, but Grace that moves God to hear prayers: He that is fervent in Prayer, prays much, though he ſpeak but little. Let not your words and matter exceed your affections, and then pray and ſpare not; otherwiſe break off, the ſooner the better.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> Hate the ſinne you pray againſt, and love the Grace you pray for.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Hate the ſinne you pray againſt; a man cannot pray heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily for the pardon of (and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170392:33"/>ſtrength againſt) thoſe ſinnes that he does not hate: but when the ſinne of his heart is the grief of his ſoul, now may he exſpect par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.<note place="margin">1 Kings 8.38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>When every one ſhall know the plague of his own heart, then hear thou in Heaven, &amp;c. When every one ſhall know his own fore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 6.29, 30.</note> 
               <hi>and his own grief, then hear thou in Heaven, &amp;c.</hi> When a man may pray for pardon of ſinne, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hatred of it, and heart grief for it, then may he with comfort expect pardon.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Love the Grace you pray for: A man cannot pray fervently, for that he doth not love heartily. Saith our Saviour to the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>If thou kneweſt the gift of God, &amp;c. thou wouldſt have asked, &amp;c.</hi> If thou hadſt known me, and the worth of the Grace that I give, this would have quickned thy deſires to have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170392:34"/>asked of me, and then I would have given thee living water. The ſence of the worth of grace draws love to it, and theſe ſtrengthen the deſires of it. And ſo much for this fourth thing propounded, the duties or graces requiſite in Prayer.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Fifthly.</note> I ſhall ſhew you the geſtures that are to be uſed in Prayer: And I finde in Scripture principally theſe four; Kneeling, ſifting up and ſpreading forth the Hands, lifting up the Eyes, and for men to uncover their Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Kneeling; This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>O come let us worſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 95.6.</note> 
               <hi>and bow down, and kneel before the Lord our Maker.</hi> Here we ſee, that religious kneeling is part of Divine worſhip. It is but equity, that he that made the body ſhould be worſhipped by, or with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170392:34"/>the body: And for as much as Jeſus Chriſt hath redeemed our Bodies as well as our Souls, he ought to be worſhiped with our Bodies as well as Soules: And ſo the Apoſtle argues,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>For ye are bought with a price, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore glorifie God.</hi> Our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and ſoules are Gods, not onely by right of Creation, but alſo by right of Redemption, therefore we muſt glorifie God by worſhiping of him with our bodies, as well as our ſouls. And we finde in Scripture divers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for kneeling in Prayer. <hi>David,</hi> he kneeled in prayer:<note place="margin">Pſal 95.6. 1 King. 8.54. Dan. 6.10.</note> and <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſonne he kneeled on his knees in prayer: <hi>Daniel,</hi> he kneeled on his knees in prayer: <hi>Stephen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 7.60.</note> he kneeled down and prayed: <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9.14.</note> he kneeled down and prayed: Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20.36.</note> he kneeled down and prayed, he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170392:35"/>bowed his knees to the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.14.</note> and he in <hi>Mark</hi> 10.17.<note place="margin">Mark 10.17.</note> came kneeling to our Saviour. And we find that all the people, men, women, and children kneeled down and prayed.<note place="margin">Acts 21.5</note> All theſe Examples you have for kneeling in prayer: Take one more, who is the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of all patternes, our bleſſed Saviour himſelf,<note place="margin">Luke 22.41.</note> 
               <hi>He kneeled down and prayed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A ſecond Geſture uſed in Prayer, is lifting up, and ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of Hands: We muſt not onely lift up our hearts, but alſo our hands to God in Prayer. <hi>Lift up your hands in the Sanctuary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 134.2</note> 
               <hi>and bleſſe the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.8</note> 
               <hi>I will that men pray every where, lifting up pure hands.</hi> And for this geſture alſo, we have ſeveral Examples; <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 17.11, 12.</note> he held up his hands to God in prayer: And <hi>David</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170392:35"/>that the lifting up of his hads to God (in Prayer) may be acceptable, as an evening ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice:<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.2 2 Chron. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> he ſpread forth his hands to God in prayer, and ſo did <hi>Ezra:</hi> And I conceive this lifting up of the hands in Prayer, is to be uſed, to ſignifie theſe two things: Firſt, that the heart is lift up to God; ſaith the Prophet in the <hi>Lamentations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.41</note> 
               <hi>Let us lift up our heart, with our hands, unto God in the Heavens.</hi> That is, let let your hearts be lift up as well as your hands. Some lift up their hands while their hearts hang down in Prayer; but doe you lift up your hearts firſt, and then lift up your hands, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your hearts are alſo lift up to God.<note place="margin">Job. 11.13</note> 
               <hi>If thou prepare thine heart, and ſtreach out thine hands towards him:</hi> Streach out thy hands to him, to ſignifie thou haſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170392:36"/> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> already given thy heart to him in Prayer. Secondly, lifting up the hands in prayer, it ſignifies our depending upon Gods power to help and aſſiſt us in time of need: As a Child that is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of falling, he ſtretcheth out his hand to his Father for help: So in Prayer, the hands are lift up to God, as a ſigne of expecting help from him. Saith <hi>David, Hear the voice of my ſupplication,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 28.2.</note> 
               <hi>when I cry unto thee, when I lift up my hands towards thy holy Oracle.</hi> By ſtretching forth our hands to God in Prayer, we doe as it were tell him that we depend wholly upon him for help, favour, mercy and pardon, and that unleſſe he help and deliver us, we are loſt and undone for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A third geſture in Prayer, is lifting up of the Eyes: For this we have the example of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170392:36"/>Saviour,<note place="margin">John 11.41. Joh. 17.1. Pſal. 123.1, 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>He lift up his Eyes and prayed.</hi> And ſo did <hi>David, Unto thee lift I up mine Eyes.</hi> This lifting up of the Eyes in prayer, it hath the ſame ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with the former, of lifting up of the Hands: Lifting up the Eye, it ſignifies the eye of Faith and Hope, depending upon Gods help and aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt Geſture in prayer,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> is for men to have the Head uncovered: This the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teacheth, where he ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Corin. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>Every man praying or propheſying, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his head covered, diſhonoureth his head.</hi> I read the Turkes nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kneel, nor uncover the Head in prayer, eſteeming it unmanly. But Chriſtians in all places, and in all Ages have uſed both theſe geſtures in Prayer: And for men to be uncovered in Prayer, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this reaſon holds good; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170392:37"/>it is uſual amongſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, when Inferiours are ſpeaking to Superiours, to have their heads uncovered, to manifeſt their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; and it is a ſhame, and a diſhonour to a man to doe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. So when poor weak frail mortal man is by Prayer ſpeaking to the great God of Heaven and Earth, it is requiſite he ſhould manifeſt his reverence and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto God, by being bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed; otherwiſe, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, he diſhonoureth his Head.</p>
            <p>But may ſome Object,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> Will you tie us to theſe geſtures, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we finde that Gods people ſtood and prayed?<note place="margin">Neh. 9.2.</note> And the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican</hi> and <hi>Phariſee</hi> ſtood and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Luke 18 11, 13. Heb. 11.21.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> leaned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſtaffe and worſhiped.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, I doe not tie you at all times to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170392:37"/>before mentioned, No:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For firſt, outward geſtures may be omitted when they ſhall hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us in the ſervice of God: As for example, If the Miniſter ſhould kneel, the people could not ſo well hear him; and the ſeats of ſome in the Church are ſo placed, that if they ſhould kneel, they ſhould not hear the Miniſter. In this caſe ſtanding is better then kneeling, becauſe God accepts not of that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture that hinders us in his ſervice. And it is like in this caſe,<note place="margin">Neh. 9.2, 3, 4.</note> the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> did ſtand and pray, and the people alſo ſtood and prayed. And for the <hi>Publican</hi> and <hi>Phariſee,</hi> their prayers were but ſhort Ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, not the ſolemne ſetting themſelves to the dutie of Prayer: therefore their example in ſtanding can be no rule for our practice in the ſet perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170392:38"/>of the duty. Secondly, outward geſtures may be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted when we cannot uſe them without evident danger of health, or without ſuch pain to the body as trouble and diſtract the mind in Gods ſervice. Some cannot kneel in prayer, through bodily weakneſſe and infirmities; in this caſe God perfers mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſacrifice.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.7.</note> And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect old <hi>Iacob</hi> roſe upon his bed,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.21.</note> leaned upon his ſtaffe and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. And ſo if a man through age, or weakneſſe, cannot be bare-headed, he may have ſome covering: Onely take this rule (in theſe caſes) if a man cannot kneel, or be bare-headed in Prayer, yet muſt he uſe ſome other bodily geſture, to ſhew as much bodily reverence as he can: For ſo did <hi>Iacob,</hi> who being aged, and ready to give up the Ghoſt;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170392:38"/>yet would he not lie along on his bed and pray, but he roſe up, and leaned on his ſtaffe: he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as much reverence as he could: he was not able to kneel, or ſit upright, therefore he leaned; and this geſture is given as an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his Faith. <hi>By Faith</hi> he did thus, to teach us, that thoſe that have true Faith in God, will ſhew as much bodily reverence to him in prayer as they can.</p>
            <p>If yet it be objected,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> Why may not a man ſit, or lie along, or be covered, and pray?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> If they can uſe the other Geſtures which are moſt ſutable to the duty, and yet doe not, they ſinne: For if ſitting, or lying, be as fit geſtures in Prayer as kneeling, what needed <hi>David</hi> to have roſe at midnight to performe the duty as we finde he did reſolve upon:<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.62.</note> 
               <hi>At mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170392:39"/>I will riſe to give thanks to thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.62.</note> When others were ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he was praying: and that he might apply himſelf to ſuch a poſture as was moſt ſutable to the duty, he roſe at midnight to performe it; To teach us, that a lazie poſture in the duty of Prayer is not to be uſed. As a full anſwer to all cavils, take theſe two Concluſions:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, thoſe geſtures that bring a deadneſſe and dulneſſe, and ſhew no reverence to God in the duty of Prayer, ought not to be uſed: But ſitting, lying, and for men to be covered in Prayer (when there is no infirmity, or neceſſity conſtrains them to it) brings deadneſſe, and diſcovers no reverence to God in the duty; therefore they are not to be uſed in it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, thoſe Geſtures in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170392:39"/>publick, that are of bad example to others, are not to be uſed: But ſitting, lying along, or being covered, are of bad example to others; therefore they are not to be uſed in Prayer.</p>
            <p>Now although it be my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make a general applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all in the cloſe; yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, that many in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation are defective in the geſtures of Prayer, give me leave to ſpeak a few words by way of Uſe to this, before I paſſe to the next thing propounded. And
<list>
                  <item>1. For Reprehenſion.</item>
                  <item>2. For Exhortation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, by way of Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Uſe. Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</note> is kneeling, lifting up the hands and eyes, and being bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed commanded, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in Scripture, as geſtures requiſite in Prayer? Tell me then, doe not thoſe deſerve to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170392:40"/>be reproved that neglect theſe Geſtures, or uſe the contrary: That inſtead of uſing theſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, they ſit, or lie along, and are with their Hats half off and half on; are not theſe lazie, and irreverent poſtures, more fit for thoſe that give themſelves to ſleeping, then thoſe that ſet themſelves to Prayer? If any of your Children ſhould greatly offend you, and then come and ſit down before you, or lie along, or be with their hats half off, and half on, and ask you forgiveneſſe, would you not be diſpleaſed with them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne their want of reverence? Beloved, we ought to come to God as a Father; but if we come to him with irreverent poſtures, may he not ſay unto us,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>If I be a Father, where is mine honour?</hi> More reverence becometh chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170392:40"/>to their Father. Can your Conſciences ſerve you to uſe leſſe reverence to God, then you would uſe to man? think of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for Exhortation:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Uſe. Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> I beſeech you be exhorted to uſe more reverence in Prayer. <hi>God is greatly to be feared in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 89.7.</note> 
               <hi>and to be had in reverence of all that are about him.</hi> If thou haſt grace, it will teach thee to ſerve God reverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Therefore,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> 
               <hi>Let us have grace whereby we may ſerve God with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and godly fear.</hi> God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts not of that ſervice that is not reverently performed: He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that will ſerve God accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, muſt ſerve him reverently. That man that does not behave himſelf reverently in reſpect of the outward man in Prayer, he can have no reverent nor high
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170392:41"/>eſteeme of God in his heart; for where that is, it will cauſe an humble and reverent deportment of the body. Wherefore I Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, and beſeech you, for time to come, uſe not ſuch irreverent poſtures in Prayer, as if you ſcorned the Ordinance; but let the outward poſtures of the body expreſſe the inward reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and humility of the heart: Uſe all the reverence that is ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the duty, unleſſe age, or extream weakneſſe of body diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inable thee.<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.31.</note> We finde examples in Scripture of ſitting to hear the Word, but throughout the whole Book of God, I remember not any example of ſitting in Prayer. Wherefore I beſeech you, uſe as much reverence in the duty as you can. And ſo much for this fifth thing propounded.</p>
            <p>Sixthly,<note place="margin">Sixthly.</note> I come to lay down
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170392:41"/>ſome Motivies to preſſe you to the performance of the duty of Prayer, and they ſhall be of two ſorts:
<list>
                  <item>1. The neceſſity of the Duty.</item>
                  <item>2. The benefit that comes by the performance thereof.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, of the neceſſity of the duty of Prayer.<note place="margin">Firſt.</note> It is neceſſary in theſe four repects.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it is neceſſary becauſe God hath commanded it: In the Text, and in ſeveral places throughout the Book of God, I ſhall not need to mention them; It is neceſſary we ſhould manifeſt our obedience, by yeilding to Gods commands; therefore Pray.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it is neceſſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without Prayer we can have no ſanctified uſe of the Creatures. <hi>For every creature of God is good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>and nothing to be refuſed, if it be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170392:42"/>received with thankſgiving; For it is ſanctified by the Word and Prayer.</hi> It is one thing to have the Creature, an other thing to have a Sanctified uſe of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; this is not obtained but by Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, it is neceſſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no drawing water out of the wells of Salvation, but by the bucket of faithful Prayer.<note place="margin">Iſai. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>With joy ſhall ye draw water out of the wells of ſalvation.</hi> Gods Ordinances are the wells of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and faithful Prayer is the bucket that fetcheth the water of Conſolation out of theſe wells.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> and laſtly, Prayer is neceſſary, becauſe without it we cannot obtain Gods bleſſing, but are expoſed to Gods curſe.<note place="margin">ler. 10 25. Pſal. 79.6.</note> 
               <hi>Pour out thy wrath upon the Heathen, and upon the Families that call not upon thy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170392:42"/>
            <p>A ſecond ſort of Motives to Prayer,<note place="margin">Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> ſhall be taken from the benefits that come by Prayer, and they are many.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, If you pray aright to God, you ſhall not loſe your labour, but you ſhall be ſure to ſpeed: <hi>Ask and ye ſhall have, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>I ſaid not to the houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>ſeek ye me in vain.</hi> To be ſure,<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.19.</note> if you labour in this (or in any) work of God, your labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Prayer is a ſigne of true Converſion: by this the Lord would manifeſt unto <hi>Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> that <hi>Saul</hi> was converted, and he might ſafely goe to him; <hi>For behold he prayeth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Prayer is alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Salvation: Whoſoever ſhall call upon the Name of the Lord,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.13.</note> ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170392:43"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Prayer, it is ſweet and pleaſant in Gods ears: Saith Chriſt to the Church,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14</note> 
               <hi>Let me hear thy voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 141.2 Rev. 5.8. &amp; chap. 8.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>for ſweet is thy voice.</hi> The Prayers of the Saints are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God as Incenſe and ſweet O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, for ſo they are called in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, When nothing elſe can give comfort, and eaſe the heart of grief, yet Prayer will. Saith <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.22</note> 
               <hi>I ſaid in my haſte, I am cut off before thine eyes; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, then thou heardeſt the voice of my ſupplication when I cryed unto thee.</hi> It is good to have a boſome friend; and the very opening of our grief to ſuch is an eaſe to the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, Prayer is the onely way to get the heart filled with ſpiritual Graces, as Joy,<note place="margin">John 16.24.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Ask and ye ſhall receive, that your joy may be full. Let
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170392:43"/>thoſe that ſeek thee, rejoyce and be glad in thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 40.16.</note> The Apoſtle uſes Prayer as a means by which all Grace ſhould be wrought in the <hi>Epheſians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.14. &amp; 16. to 20 ver.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, By prayer we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach into Gods preſence:<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.2.</note> God will not hide his face from his praying ſervants:<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.24</note> But of an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Job 13.16.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall not come before him.</hi> A rogue may beg without the gate, but he may not be ſuffred to come within doors: The upright ſoul that ſeeks God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 140.13.</note> ſhall dwell in his Preſence.</p>
            <p>The eighth and laſt Motive that I ſhall uſe to preſſe you to the duty of Prayer;<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> it ſhall be taken from the goodneſſe and power of God: And that doth appear in theſe four things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, he hath ſtiled himſelf a God hearing Prayer:<note place="margin">Pſal. 65.2.</note> 
               <hi>O thou that heareſt prayer, unto thee ſhall all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170392:44"/>fleſh come.</hi> And of the righteous that ſeek him,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.12</note> it is ſaid, his ears are open to their Prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, God is able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all his peoples needs: So ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.8</note> 
               <hi>God is able to make all grace to abound towards you. He is able to doe exceeding abundantly above all that we ask or think.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.20.</note> But may ſome ſay, If God be able to ſupply my need, if he be not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, what encouragement is this to Prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And therefore in the third place; Gods is as willing to hear and help his people as he is able: And this doth appear in that he ſaith, <hi>He delights to exerciſe loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>He waits that he may be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 30.18.</note> He is very pittiful,<note place="margin">Jam. 5.11.</note> and of tender mercy:<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.13.</note> 
               <hi>As a Father pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth his children.</hi> No ſooner do Gods people (in their diſtreſſe) cry unto him, but he being nigh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170392:44"/>at hand, he readily hears and helps them. <hi>The righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>cry and the Lord heareth, and delivereth them out of all their troubles; the Lord is nigh unto them that are of a broken heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, and laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> God hath made many promiſes to hear and help thoſe that pray unto him; and theſe you ſhall find in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places throughout the whole book of God. I ſhall onely mention two:<note place="margin">Iſa. 65.24.</note> 
               <hi>Before they call I will anſwer, and whiles they are yet ſpeaking I will hear. The Lord is nigh unto all that call upon him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>to all that call upon him in truth. He will fulfil the deſire of them that fear him, he alſo will hear their cry, and will ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have heard divers Motives to the duty of Prayer: Now I beſeech you, let them take impreſſion upon your hearts,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170392:45"/>whereby you may be moved to ſet upon, and be conſtant in the duty of Prayer. So much for the ſixt thing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> I come now to the ſeaventh thing propounded to be ſpoken to, and that is, The times of Prayer: Saith the Apoſtle in the words following my Text, <hi>Without ceaſing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.17.</note> or continually: I ſhall
<list>
                  <item>1. Shew you what is meant by praying continually, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing.</item>
                  <item>2. I ſhall ſhew you what are the ſpecial times for Prayer.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt of the firſt, Continually, or without ceaſing: That is,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1.When a man uſes a conſtant courſe of Praying, upon all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, in all his neceſſities. And thus did the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> pray alwayes for the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſsians;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.3.</note> that is, upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170392:45"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, (continually) That is, conſtantly without fainting, or wearineſſe.<note place="margin">Luk 18.1.</note> 
               <hi>And he ſpake a parable unto them to this end, that men ought always to pray, and not to faint.</hi> And in this ſenſe the Apoſtle prayed for the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Night and day exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> (continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) That is, every day once or twice, (though not every hour of the day) And thus the Offerings for the morning and evening Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,<note place="margin">Num. 28.4, 6.</note> are ſaid to be continuall Offerings. As <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Mephiboſheth, Thou ſhalt eat bread at my table continually:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 9.7</note> that is, every day. And in this ſenſe, it is ſaid, <hi>Job offered burnt offerings continually.</hi> And <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>He prayed to God alwaies.</hi> And the Apoſtles reſolved to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves continually to Prayer,<note place="margin">Acts 10.2.</note> and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170392:46"/>the Miniſtry of the Word.<note place="margin">Acts 6.4. 2 Theſ. 1.11.</note> And ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We pray alwayes for you.</hi> Thus you ſee what is meant by always, or continually: it is daily, all their life long.</p>
            <p>I come now in the ſecond place,<note place="margin">Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> to ſhew you the ſpecial times for Prayer. And although the heart ought to be continually carried out after God in Prayer: Yet are there ſpecial times of Prayer. As publick on the Lords Dayes, on Faſt dayes, or Thanſgiving dayes. And alſo upon private occaſions, as in time of affliction:<note place="margin">Jam. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>Is any afflicted, let him pray?</hi> But yet more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, Chriſtians ought to have ſet-times for Prayer every day: And thus <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.10</note> 
               <hi>He prayed three times a day.</hi> And ſo did <hi>David, Evening, morning, and at noon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.17</note> And you ſhall find he was yet more frequent in the work: for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170392:46"/>he ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.164.</note> 
               <hi>Seaven times a day doe I praiſe thee, becauſe of thy righteous judgements.</hi> And of <hi>Anna</hi> it is ſaid, that ſhe ſerved God with Faſting and Prayer night and day.<note place="margin">Luk. 2.37</note> But I conceive that theſe did thus upon extraordinary occaſions, and therefore can be no ſtanding rules for our practice.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay unto me then,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſt.</note> What are the ſet-times for every Chriſtians Prayers?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, they are to pray every day,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> and at leaſt twice in the day, Morning and Evening.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, every day; This is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in the fourth Petition,<note place="margin">Mat 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>Give us this day our dayly bread.</hi> And ſo we muſt pray every day, Give us this day. And this is alſo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured out unto us,<note place="margin">Exod. 29.39, 42.</note> by the every dayes burnt offering. And this <hi>David</hi> exhorts unto, and himſelf reſolves upon.<note place="margin">Pſal 96.2.</note> 
               <hi>Sing unto the Lord,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170392:47"/>bleſſe his name, ſhew forth his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from day to day:</hi> That is, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day: And ſo he reſolves, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.2</note> 
               <hi>Every day will I bleſſe thee, and I will praiſe thy name for ever and ever.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 146.2</note> 
               <hi>While I live, I will praiſe the Lord:</hi> that is, every day of my life. Thus you ſee we are to pray every day.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But ſecondly, The fitteſt time in the day for Prayer, is the Morning and Evening. In the morning, to praiſe God for the reſt of the night paſt, and to ſeek his bleſſing and protection the day following. And in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening to praiſe him for the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings received the day paſt, and to ſeek his bleſſing and protection the night approaching. This was alſo figured out unto us,<note place="margin">Exod. 29.38, 39.</note> by the offering of the two Lambs every day, one in the morning, and another in the evening.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170392:47"/>And this the Apoſtle hints us to, when he ſaith, <hi>Let us offer the ſacrifice of praiſe to God continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</hi> That is, as the Sacrifices of the Old Law were offered to God continually every morning, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very night.<note place="margin">Pſal. 92.1, 2.</note> And ſaith <hi>David, It is a good thing to give thanks unto the Lord, &amp;c. to ſhew forth thy loving kindneſſe in the morning, and thy faithfulneſſe every night.</hi> That is, it is good night by night, and morning by morning; every morning, and every night, to pray and praiſe God. And great reaſon their is why we ſhould be thus conſtant in Prayer, every morning and every night.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, Becauſe we ſtand in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall need of bleſſings, both ſpiritual and temporal; it is therefore needful that we begge them daily, every morning, and every evening.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170392:48"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, we cannot thrive, nor proſper in any of our daily callings or imployments without Gods bleſſing.<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vain that build it; except the Lord watch the City, the watchman waketh but in vain: It is in vain for you to riſe up early, to ſit up late, to eat the bread of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, &amp;c.</hi> A man may riſe early, and ſit up late, but he can never thrive without Gods bleſſing; and he cannot expect Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing without Prayer. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every day in all our labours, we ought to pray with <hi>David, Eſtabliſh the work of our hands upon us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 90.17</note> 
               <hi>yea, the work of our hands eſtabliſh thou it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, We are ſubject every day to decay in grace; and there is no means to obtain grace, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve grace, or increaſe in grace,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170392:48"/>like this of Prayer. And therefore the Apoſtle did not ceaſe to pray for the <hi>Coloſsians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.9, 10, 11.</note> that they might be filled with all grace. Prayer is as the food whereby graces are preſerved, revived and increaſed: As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we take daily food to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, revive, and ſtrengthen the body; ſo we muſt daily uſe Prayer (this ſpiritual food) that our ſouls may be preſerved and nouriſhed up unto Eternal life; therefore pray every day.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, It is needful we pray every day continually, becauſe we have the Devil every day conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, as our adverſary, like a roaring Lyon ſeeking to devour us.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> And there is no weapon like that of faithful Prayer to withſtand him. And hence it is that our Saviour Chriſt bid his Diſciples <hi>watch and pray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.41</note> 
               <hi>that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170392:49"/>they enter not into temption.</hi> And in the Lords Prayer we are to pray every day, <hi>Lead us not</hi> (or ſuffer us not to be led) <hi>into temptation.</hi> It is a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage given to Satan, to neglect the duty of Prayer; therefore pray every day.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, We are prone daily (and as it were every moment) to ſinne againſt God: And there is no means like that of Prayer to prevent it. Hence it is that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> prays,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.13.</note> 
               <hi>Keep back thy ſervant alſo from preſumptuous ſinnes, let not them have dominion over me. Order my ſteps in thy word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.133.</note> 
               <hi>and let not any iniquity have the dominion over me.</hi> While we live in this world, we cannot be free from ſinne, but Prayer is a ſpecial means to free us from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of ſinne. While we are in the body, ſinne will be there;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170392:49"/>yet ſhall it not raign in our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal bodies, ſo as we ſhall obey it in the luſts thereof,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> if we dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeek God for pardon of it, and ſtrength againſt it; and that leads me to</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> The ſixth and laſt Reaſon, why we are to pray every day; It is becauſe we have need con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to begge pardon of ſin. We have not more need of dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread to preſerve the body from periſhing, than of daily pardon of ſinne that the Soul may not periſh: And therefore it followes in the Lords Prayer after,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Give us this day our daily bread, Forgive us our treſpaſſes.</hi> It is requiſite we ſhould, begge pardon in the morning for the ſinnes of the night paſt, and we ſhould begge pardon at night. for the ſinnes of the day paſt. And ſo continue ſeeking of God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170392:50"/>day, that our ſinnes may be pardoned, that our Souls may be ſaved. And ſo much for this ſeventh thing propounded; the times of Prayer.</p>
            <p>I come now to the eighth and laſt thing propounded;<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> and that is to anſwer divers Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob∣jection. </seg>1</label> Firſt, ſome may object, It is to no purpoſe to pray:
<list>
                  <item>1.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.8.</note> Becauſe God knoweth our wants.</item>
                  <item>2.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.11.</note> He hath Decreed what ſhall befal every man.</item>
                  <item>3.<note place="margin">Phil. 4.6.</note> He is ready to give us what is fit for us.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> I Anſwer, firſt, although God knoweth our wants, yet it is his will we ſhould make them known to him by Prayer. Saith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Let your requeſts be made known unto God.</hi> Chriſt knew that blinde <hi>Bartimeus</hi> had need
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170392:50"/>of his ſight, and yet he would have him to pray for it, before he would give him it:<note place="margin">Mark 10.51, 52.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſaid unto him, What wilt thou that I ſhould doe unto thee? the blinde man ſaid unto him, Lord that I might receive my ſight, and immediately he received his fight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, As God determins what he will doe, he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined alſo that Prayer ſhall be the means whereby we ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain what he hath determined to give us: God promiſes to give a new heart, and a new ſpirit, with many other bleſſings, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 36. and yet in the 37 <hi>Verſe</hi> he ſaith, <hi>For all this I will be inquired by the houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 36.37.</note> God promiſes the reſtauration of <hi>Iſrael, Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> 31. yet he ſaith in the nineth Verſe,<note place="margin">Jer. 31.9.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall come with weeping, and with ſupplications
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170392:51"/>will I lead them.</hi> They ſhall be led out of their captivity, but it ſhall be as an anſwer of Prayers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this praying doth not at all derogate from Gods goodneſſe and readineſſe to give; but it rather demonſtrateth his goodneſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1.In that he ſaith, but <hi>ask and have.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2.In that he alone ſtirs us up to pray, to the end he may doe us good:<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.17</note> 
               <hi>Thou prepareſt their heart, thou wilt cauſe thine ear to hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3.God will have us pray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gives bleſſings, becauſe he delighteth in the work of his own Spirit in us.<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14</note> 
               <hi>Le me hear thy voice, for it is ſweet,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to his Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> God knoweth that his bleſſings will be then moſt ſweet and comfortable to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170392:51"/>us, when we have obtained them by Prayer. Saith <hi>Hannah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>For this Child I prayed, and the Lord hath given me my petition which I asked of him.</hi> When mercy comes as an anſwer of Prayer, this engages the Soul to love God, and quicken up the heart yet more and more to ſeek him; ſo it was with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>I love the Lord becauſe he hath heard my voice, and my ſupplication: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath enclined his ear unto me, therefore will I call upon him as long as I live.</hi> You ſee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God heard his prayer, he reſolves to go on in this courſe of praying as long as he lived. And thus you ſee, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Objection, it is to good purpoſe we ſhould pray.</p>
            <p>Again, it may be Objected,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note> It is needleſſe to pray, becauſe the good ſucceſſe of things depends
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170392:52"/>upon ſecond cauſes, and natural means God uſeth to work by, as Phyſick, Bread, and the like.</p>
            <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> this is a moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and heatheniſh Objection: For although God works by means, yet is it not in the means without Gods bleſſing to do us good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, It is a ſinne to uſe the means without ſeeking of God: as <hi>Aſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 16.12.</note> 
               <hi>In his diſeaſe he ſought not the Lord, but to the Phyſitian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, It is a ſinne alſo, and tempting of God to pray, and yet neglect the means. You ſhall finde that God blameth <hi>Moſes</hi> for reſting upon Prayer, with the neglect of the meanes. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>wherefore cryeſt thou unto me? ſpeak unto the Children of Iſrael that they goe forward.</hi> Why doſt thou pray and ſtand ſtill, and doſt not
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170392:52"/>uſe the means? March on, doe not only pray, but uſe the means. He that prays, and uſes not the means, tempts God; and ſaith Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> But when we pray to him, and truſt in him, in the uſe of means, then (and not till then) may we expect Gods bleſſing. <hi>Ariſe therefore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 22.16.</note> 
               <hi>and be doing, and the Lord be with thee.</hi> For all our labours are to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe without Gods bleſſing:<note place="margin">1 Chron. 3.7.</note> and our ordinary food cannot nouriſh us without Gods bleſſing.<note place="margin">Mat. 4.4.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude, although God work by ſecondary cauſes, yet thoſe doe it not without his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. And we cannot expect Gods bleſſing without Prayer. It is therefore needful, in the uſe of all means, to pray to God for a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It may be Objected,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170392:53"/>That they that never pray, doe as well as they that pray moſt: What neede therefore is there of this conſtant praying?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> it is moſt falſe to ſay thoſe that pray not, doe as well as thoſe that pray moſt: For,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, The bleſſings that thoſe that never pray, receive, they are but temporal.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note> 
               <hi>He maketh his ſunne to ſhine on the evil, and on the good; and ſendeth rain on the juſt and the unjuſt.</hi> But Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that pray unto him, are <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all ſpiritual bleſsings in heavenly things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Thoſe that pray not, can have no aſſurance of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the outward comforts they have;<note place="margin">Job 20.15 to ver. 19.</note> God hath threatned to blaſt upon them: But thoſe that pray, have a promiſe to build upon, yea, many promiſes; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170392:53"/>this,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10</note> 
               <hi>They that ſeek the Lord, ſhall not want any good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. And laſtly, They that pray not, have no right to any outward thing they do enjoy, neither can they have any ſound comfort in it. Saith <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1.32</note> 
               <hi>The proſperity of fooles ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> They have no right to it, they ſhall be the worſe for it. But leſt I ſhould be miſtaken, when I ſay wicked men that pray not, have no right to the outward things they doe enjoy, my meaning is, they have no right to them by the vertue of any promiſe; neither can they have a ſanctified uſe of them: but they have a right to them in regard of Gods free bounty;<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.14</note> for he giveth them the things of this world as their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and it is all the comfort they ſhall ever have. <hi>Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.25.</note> 
               <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170392:54"/>that thou in thy life time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivedſt thy good things.</hi> You ſee the things of this world are called the wicked mans portion, his good things; therefore they have a right to them, and no man ought in the leaſt to wrong or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure them in them. But on the contrary, Gods faithful ſervants that pray unto him, they have a right too, and a ſanctified uſe of all the bleſſings they doe enjoy. Firſt they have a right to them, ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>All things are yours, and ye are Chriſts.</hi> And ſecondly, by Prayer, every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſanctified unto them for their good.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.4.5.</note> It muſt needs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be farre better with him that prays, than with him that pray not.</p>
            <p>But may ſome ſay,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note> I am unable to pray, I would pray, but I want Faith, and the Spirit of Prayer.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170392:54"/>
            <p>I Anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> It is a good ſigne in the ſenſe of the want of Grace to deſire it. Let not this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore detain thee from the Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For firſt, thou maieſt have Faith though thou feeleſt it not. In Chriſts feeling his Father had forſaken him.<note place="margin">Mat. 27.46</note> If thou mourneſt for nothing more then the want of Faith, it is a ſigne thou haſt it. In the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Mar. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>The Father of the Child cryed out with tears, Lord I believe, help thou my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief.</hi> If thou deſireſt nothing ſo much as to believe, it is a ſigne thou haſt Faith: For as luſting after a woman is Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.28.</note> ſo luſting after Chriſt is Faith, becauſe God accepts of the will for the deed; therefore let not this diſcourage thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a man may have the Spirit of prayer, and pray ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually and acceptably, when in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170392:55"/>his own feeling his heart is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indiſpoſed to prayer. Thus it was with <hi>Aſaph,</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.2, 3, 4. <hi>My ſoul refuſed to be comforted; I remembred God, and was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, &amp;c. I am ſo troubled that I cannot ſpeak.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 77.1.</note> Yet for all this, <hi>verſe</hi> the firſt, God gave ear unto him. And ſaith <hi>David, I am feeble, and ſore broken, I have roared by reaſon of the diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe of my heart.</hi> And yet in the next Verſe he ſaith, Lord, all my deſire is before thee, and my groaning is not hid from thee.<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.8, 9.</note> O how ſadly did <hi>Hezekiah</hi> mourn,<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.14. &amp; ver. 5.</note> and chatter in his Prayers! yet God heard, and anſwered him. It is not the brokenneſſe of our expreſſions that hinders the anſwer of our Prayers, if the heart be throughly broken for ſinne: No, no, when words fail, tears will ſpeak, and they have a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170392:55"/>voice in Gods ears. Saith <hi>David, The Lord hath heard the voice of my weeping.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 6.8. Pſal. 39.12.</note> 
               <hi>Hold not thy peace at my tears. Thou telleſt my wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 56.8.</note> 
               <hi>put thou my tears in thy bottle, are they not in thy book?</hi> Yes, yes, beloved, all the tears that Gods ſervants ſhed before him for their ſinnes, they are all put into his Bottle, and recorded in his Book. Therefore let not the ſenſe of thine own weakneſſe and inability keep thee from thy duty: but goe to God, mourn for thy wants, and begge ſupply of him, and he will anſwer thee.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I would fain pray;<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note> but I am ſo ſinful, and unworthy a wretch, I dare not: I know <hi>God heareth not ſinners:</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 9.31</note> yet ſuch a one am I, and therefore I dare not pray.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> Take heed thou doſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170392:56"/>not miſtake the Text, nor thy condition. If God heareth no man that ſinneth, then no man ſhould be ever heard of God; <hi>For there is not a juſt man upon earth that doth good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.20.</note> 
               <hi>and ſinneth not.</hi> And therefore for the meaning of the Text, know that the ſinners that God will not hear, They are ſuch as live and lie in their ſinnes without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, rejecting the worſhip and will of God: ſuch ſinners as theſe God heareth not; he will not accept of a good motion from ſuch a bad mouth: but as it followeth in that place,<note place="margin">John 9 31.</note> 
               <hi>If any man be a worſhipper of God, and doth his will, him he heareth.</hi> In every Nation,<note place="margin">Acts 10.35.</note> he that feareth God, and worketh righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is accepted with him. But for a further, and fuller anſwer to the Objection, know</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170392:56"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the ſenſe of thy finful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and unworthineſſe ſhould not keep thee from thy duty of praying.<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> cryed out of his ſinnes, that they were more then the haires of his head, yet he prayed. And <hi>Ezra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 9.6.</note> by reaſon of his ſinnes, was aſhamed to lift up his face to God, yet he prayed. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had a deep ſenſe of his ſinnes;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15. Epheſ. 3.8. Acts 9.12.</note> he ſaid he was <hi>the chief of all Sinners,</hi> and <hi>leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints:</hi> yet, <hi>behold, he prayeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The more heinous our ſinnes are, the more need have we to ſeek to God for mercy. They that be whole, need not a Phyſician, but they that are ſick.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, The ſenſe of ſinne makes us more capable of mercy; none more welcome to God, then they that are moſt ſenſible of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170392:57"/>their ſinnes. See it in five exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, The woman that was cured of her bloody iſſue, ſhe came behind Chriſt, as being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to look him on the face, and ſhe deſired but to touch the hem of his garment,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.20, 21, 22.</note> yet ſhe was cured.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The <hi>Centurion,</hi> who thought himſelf not worthy to come to Chriſt, or that Chriſt ſhould come under his roof,<note place="margin">Luke 7.6, 7, 10.</note> yet his requeſt was granted.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, The <hi>Prodigal,</hi> who acknowledged to his Father his ſinnes, and unworthineſſe to be called his ſonne;<note place="margin">Luke 15.20, 21, 22.</note> yet his Father embraced him, and entertained him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, The <hi>Publican,</hi> who in the ſenſe of his own unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, durſt not lift up his eyes to Heaven; and to ſhew his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170392:57"/>indignation againſt himſelf for his ſinnes, he ſmote upon his breaſt; yet was he juſtified,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.13, 14.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted for his ſinnes, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fifth and laſt example is the woman of <hi>Canaan;</hi> ſhe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged her ſelf to be a Dog;<note place="margin">Mat. 15.27, 28.</note> yet her prayer was anſwered. By all which examples, you ſee, that thoſe that are moſt ſenſible of their ſinnes, are moſt welcome to God. It is not ſo much ſinne as privy pride, that keep men from the duty of Prayer: As a begger, he is in want, and would fain have relief, but pride keeps him from begging.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> Know it is not ſo much the greatneſſe of thy ſinnes, as the want of Faith that keep thee off from ſeeking Gods mercy. And this ſinne of unbelief, is a greater ſin then
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170392:58"/>all thy other ſinnes thou art guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of; becauſe it makes thee to lie under the guilt and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all thy other ſinnes.<note place="margin">Joh. 16.9. chap. 3. 36. Heb. 3.12.</note> It is the root of all other ſinnes. It is ſuch a ſinne as rejects the remedy of Chriſts blood, by which they ſhould obtain pardon of ſinne. Therefore have Faith in God, and let not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your ſinnes hinder you from the performance of your Duty.</p>
            <p>Sixthly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. Anſw.</note> I have prayed, but I can find no anſwer.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this I ſhall ſhew you how many ways God anſwers his peoples Prayers, that ſo you be not miſtaken, in thinking God doth not anſwer your Prayers, when they are anſwered, and you take no notice of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, God anſwers prayers, when he grants the thing that is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170392:58"/>begged in Prayer: And thus God anſwered <hi>Hannah</hi> when ſhe prayed for a child.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.27.</note> And thus God anſwered <hi>Solomon</hi> when he prayed for wiſdome.<note place="margin">1 King. 3.9, 12.</note> It may be God hath not thus heard thy prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, God anſwers prayers when what is asked is denyed, and a better thing is granted. So <hi>Abraham</hi> begged <hi>Iſhmael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.19, 20.</note> and he gave him <hi>Iſaack.</hi> So the Diſciples asked when the kingdome ſhould be reſtored to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> Chriſt deny them that,<note place="margin">Acts 1.6, 7, 8.</note> and gives them power to be witneſſes to him. So the Cripple, he asked an Almes,<note place="margin">Acts 3.3, 6.</note> and he had his limbs reſtored to him. So God many times denies the thing is asked, but gives a better thing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, God anſwers prayers when nothing at all is granted; and yet God ſtrengthens the Soul
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170392:59"/>with his grace, to bear the want of it. Such an anſwer had <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 138.3</note> 
               <hi>In the day when I cryed, thou anſweredſt me with ſtrength in my ſoul.</hi> And thus Chriſt was heard in his ſufferings,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.9.</note> when he prayed he was ſupported. And thus the Apoſtle was anſwered, when he prayed to be delivered from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans buffetings;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>The grace of God was ſufficient for him.</hi> If God anſwer thee thus, ſay not thou haſt loſt thy labour in praying, for this is a gracious anſwer of Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, God anſwer prayers, although thy particular requeſt be not granted; yet if thou feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy heart, after prayer, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and thy inward comfort and aſſurance of Gods favour increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thereby: This is ſuch an anſwer as is beſt of all, when ſpiritual joy is increaſed by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170392:59"/>prayer.<note place="margin">Joh. 16.24.</note> 
               <hi>Ask</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that your joy may be full.</hi> Although <hi>Davids</hi> prayer was not anſwered for the good of his enemies,<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.13</note> yet his prayer returned into his own boſom; he had the inward comfort of it. And this is the meaning of that promiſe to prayer,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.6, 7</note> 
               <hi>Let your requeſts be made known unto God, and the peace of God, which paſſeth all underſtanding, ſhall keep your hearts and minds through Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Your hearts and mindes ſhall be kept ſtayed upon Chriſt: And this is a ſweet anſwer of Prayers.</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> God anſwer prayers, when he does not grant the things we have prayed for, or thoſe inward comforts of his ſpirit, yet he make us able to continue praying: this ſtrength is a work and fruit of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit helpeth our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170392:60"/>&amp;c.</hi> So long as thou canſt pray with ſuch ſtrivings, it is impoſſible God ſhould neglect thee. Yet further know, That God ſometimes grants our prayers as a Judgement; and ſometimes he denies them as a Mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, God ſometimes anſwers prayers as a Judgement; and ſo he gave the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> their own deſires,<note place="margin">Pſa. 78.29, 30, 31.</note> and withall his wrath ſeazed on them to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, God ſometimes denies to anſwer prayers as a Mercy:<note place="margin">Job 6.8, 9.</note> And ſo he denied <hi>Jobs</hi> requeſt, when he deſired God would deſtroy him, and cut him off.<note place="margin">Jona. 4.8.</note> And ſo <hi>Jonah,</hi> he wiſhed he might die; God denies his requeſt as a Mercy.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh and laſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is this,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note> I can find no
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170392:60"/>good by praying, but I find I am rarher the worſe.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> Thus we find in Scripture Gods ſervants com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining;<note place="margin">Job 30.20, 21.</note> ſaith <hi>Iob, I cryed unto thee, and thou regardeſt me not; thou art become cruel to me.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.3.</note> 
               <hi>I am weary of my crying, my throat is dryed, mine eyes fail while I wait for my God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 80.4.</note> 
               <hi>How long wilt thou be angry with the prayers of thy peoples.</hi> And <hi>Habakkuk,</hi> he cryed out,<note place="margin">Hab. 1.2</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, how long ſhall I cry, and thou wilt not hears.</hi> But for further anſwer, know, that God may doe thus, and it may be out of love to thee: As</p>
            <p>Firſt, It may be God ſeeth it better for thee to want that thou prayeſt for, then to have it: the promiſe is,<note place="margin">Pſa. 30.10 Mat. 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>They that ſeek the Lord, ſhall not want any good thing.</hi> If thou ſhouldeſt have it, it may be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170392:61"/>God ſeeth it not good for thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, It may be God ſeeth it not good for thee to have it yet;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.11.</note> every thing is beautiful in his time,<note place="margin">Luke 1.7, 13.</note> (or ſeaſon.) <hi>Zachary</hi> prayed for a child, but God gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not his requeſt till he was old; that ſo God might have the more glory by it.<note place="margin">John 11.3, 6, 15, 40 ver.</note> So Chriſt delayed to anſwer <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi>'s requeſt concerning their brother <hi>Lazarus,</hi> that ſo God might have the more glory in the cloſe.<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.18.</note> The Lord waits that he may be gracious. Gods delayes are no denials, his time is the beſt time.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. And laſtly, It may be God heareth thee, but thou perceiveſt it not.<note place="margin">Dan. 10.12.</note> So it was with <hi>Daniel;</hi> the firſt day he prayed, his prayer was anſwered, but he did not know it till afterwards. And
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170392:61"/>the cauſes why men perceive not Gods anſwer of prayers, may be theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, It may be they are heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of Gods anſwers: Saith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, I will hear what the Lord will ſpeak.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 85.8.</note> I will attentively mark what God will ſay; and for want of this, God hears many times, and they obſerve it not.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſometimes God anſwer prayers, but anguiſh and trouble of mind is the cauſe why men take no notice of it. So it was with <hi>Iob, If I had called,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 9.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and he had anſwered me, yet would I not believe that he had harkned to my voice: For he breaketh me with a tempeſt, &amp;c.</hi> As the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>They hearkned not to</hi> Moſes <hi>for anguiſh of ſpirit.</hi> So many times God anſwers his peoples prayers; but anguiſh and trouble of mind
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170392:62"/>is the cauſe why they regard it not.</p>
            <p>And thus I have gone through the eight things I propounded at firſt concerning Prayer. I have ſhewed you,
<list>
                  <item>1. What Prayer is.</item>
                  <item>2. The ſeveral Kindes of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>3. The Preparations to Prayer.</item>
                  <item>4. The Duties in it.</item>
                  <item>5. The Geſtures of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>6. The Motives to Prayer.</item>
                  <item>7. The Times of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>8. And laſtly, I have anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed divers Objections concerning Prayer.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to make Uſe and Application of all that hath been ſaid. And the Uſes ſhall be
<list>
                  <item>1. For Inſtruction.</item>
                  <item>2. For Reprehenſion.</item>
                  <item>3. For Conſolation.</item>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170392:62"/>
                  <item>4. And laſtly, For Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Uſe ſhall be for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Uſe. Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> And what hath been ſaid, may Inſtruct us:
<list>
                  <item>1. Concerning the right man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of praying.</item>
                  <item>2. Concerning the power and efficacy of Prayer.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We may be inſtructed in the right manner of Prayer.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct.</note> Ye heard in the Definition of prayer, that it is a pouring out of the heart and ſoul to God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt then, It lets us ſee that dead, dull, formal, heartleſſe Prayers are not pleaſing unto God. If we lift up our hands and eyes to God, and not our hearts and ſoules, we can have no comfortable hopes of being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. This was that which gave <hi>David</hi> confidence of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwered in his Prayer:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170392:63"/>
               <hi>For I lift up my ſoul unto thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 14.38</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce the ſoul of thy ſervant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 86.4.</note> 
               <hi>for unto thee O Lord, doe I lift up my ſoul.</hi> Cold heartleſſe prayers are ſinful prayers. Obſerve this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore as a certain truth, in prayer; the colder the ſutour, the greater thr ſinner.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, It lets us ſee, that wicked men that have not the Spirit of God, cannot pleaſe God in their praying. True prayer is a work of Gods ſpirit, and ſo floweth from the ſpirit and heart of man (as ye have heard:)<note place="margin">Prov. 15.8</note> And therefore the heartleſſe prayers of wicked men are abomination un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. Their cryes are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his eſteeme then the how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of beaſts. Saith the Lord, <hi>They have not cryed unto me with their heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 7.14</note> 
               <hi>when they howled upon their beds.</hi> Their cryes in Gods ears, are no better then the cryes
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170392:63"/>of a Dog when they cut off his neck.<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.3.</note> Thus odious are the Prayers of wicked and ungodly men in Gods eſteeme.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A ſecond Uſe of Inſtruction, Is to let us ſee the power of Prayer.<note place="margin">Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> I told you in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to prayer, That by prayer we obtain whatſoever we ask at the hands of God. I ſhall now ſhew you ſeveral Examples in Scripture of the power of Prayer.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Jam. 5.17, 18.</note> By prayer <hi>Elias</hi> ſtaied the Rain 3 yeers, and again obtained rain.<note place="margin">1 King. 17.21, 22.</note> By Prayer alſo he reſtored to life the Widowes ſonne. And by Prayer he obtained Fire from Heaven to deſtroy the Captains,<note place="margin">2 King. 1.10 to 13.</note> and their Fifties.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2 King. 2.9, 10.</note> By Prayer <hi>Eliſha</hi> had the ſpirit of <hi>Elias</hi> doubled upon him. By Prayer he raiſed from death the <hi>Shunamites</hi> ſonne. And he
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170392:64"/>prayed,<note place="margin">2 King. 6.17, 18.</note> and his Servants eyes were opened, and his Enemies ſmote with blindneſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Gen. 21.17, to 20.</note> By Prayer <hi>Hagars</hi> eyes were opened, whereby ſhe ſaw a Well to refreſh her and her ſon. And by Prayer <hi>Sampſon</hi> had wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of a Jawbone to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and revive them.<note place="margin">Judg. 15.18, 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.18.</note> By Prayer, <hi>Samuel</hi> procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Thunder to puniſh the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">Ioſh. 10.12, 13.</note> By Prayer <hi>Joſhua</hi> cauſed the Sunne and Moon to ſtand ſtill a whole day.<note place="margin">2 King. 20.11.</note> And by Prayer <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cauſed the ſunne to goe back tenne degrees.</p>
            <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.19, &amp;c.</note> By Prayer <hi>Lot</hi> ſaved <hi>Zoar,</hi> when the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah</hi> were burnt with fire from Heaven.</p>
            <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Job 42.8, 9, 10.</note> By Prayer <hi>Iob</hi> pacified the Wrath of God, being kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Friends, and obtained
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170392:64"/>a double Portion of that he loſt.</p>
            <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Exod. 8, &amp; 9 chap.</note> By Prayer <hi>Moſes</hi> moved God to take away many Plagues that were brought upon the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, That I may not be too tedious, I ſhall mention ſome of the multitude of Deliverances that are mentioned in Scripture, which were procured as an anſwer of Prayer. By Prayer <hi>Iacob</hi> was delivered from the wrath of <hi>Eſau.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.11, 12.</note> By Prayer the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were delivered out of <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod 3.7, 8.</note> By Prayer <hi>Ioſsiah</hi> was delivered from the Plagues threatned to come upon him.<note place="margin">2 King. 22.19, 21.</note> By Prayer <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> was delivered from the <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Amorites.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.12, 22.</note> By Prayer the three Children were delivered from the Fiery Furnate.<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> By Prayer <hi>Daniel</hi> was delivered from the Den of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.<note place="margin">Dan 6.22.</note>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170392:65"/>By Prayer <hi>Ionah</hi> was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of the Whales belly.<note place="margin">Jona. 2.10.</note> By Prayer <hi>Nineveh</hi> was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Judgement threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.<note place="margin">Jona. 3.10.</note> By Prayer <hi>Iehoahaz</hi> was delivered from the oppreſſing hand of the King of <hi>Syria.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 13.4, 5.</note> By Prayer <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> was delivered from the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 33.11, 12, 13.</note> By Prayer <hi>Peter</hi> was delivered out of Priſon.<note place="margin">Acts 12.5. &amp;c.</note> And by Prayer alſo <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were delivered out of Priſon.<note place="margin">Acts 16.25, 26.</note> O the Power of Prayer! O the many Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous things that have been done by Prayer! I could inſtance in many examples that I have read in Hiſtory, but I forbare to mention them; let thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly mentioned be ſufficient. And ſo much for this firſt Uſe which hath been for Inſtruction.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Uſe. Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond Uſe, which is for Reprehenſion. It is
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170392:65"/>the duty of the people of God to pray, and that conſtantly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, in the manner that hath been before mentioned. Then here come divers perſons to be reprehended.</p>
            <p>Firſt, thoſe that pray not at all;<note place="margin">Firſt.</note> Certainly it is a moſt grievous ſinne to be ever in the neglect of this duty. It is given as a note of a moſt wicked and ungodly perſon not to call upon God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.4, 5.</note> Wicked men will have nothing to doe with God, and God will have nothing to doe with them: They caſt off God, and God will caſt off them. Whoſoever they be that goe on in the conſtant neglect of this duty, they are expoſed to Gods wrath and curſe:<note place="margin">Jer. 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>Pour out thy wrath upon the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that know thee not, and upon the Families that call not upon thy Name.</hi> They who neglect
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170392:66"/>Prayer, expoſe themſelves to all manner of ſinnes and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for Prayer is the onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to prevent ſinne. Saith Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.46.</note> 
               <hi>Pray, leſt ye enter into temptation.</hi> And therefore he that neglects to pray often, will lie open to all aſſaults of Satan, and be in danger of utter falling away from all goodneſſe, into all manner of ſinne and lewdneſſe, and hereby expoſe himſelf to Gods eternal Curſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> Thoſe are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, that are laſie and ſluggiſh in Prayer. Some never pray till they be in bed; others com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to ſuch Geſtures as make them ſleepy in Prayer.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.41.</note> Is this to watch and pray? Is not this laſie ſluggiſh praying, a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent doing of Gods work? And can you ever think God will be pleaſed with ſuch kind
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170392:66"/>of ſervice? No, no, in ſtead of a bleſſing, it will bring a curſe upon thee: Saith the Prophet, <hi>Curſed is he that doth the work of the Lord deceitfully:</hi> That is,<note place="margin">Jer. 48.10.</note> that doth it negligently, ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, ſlowly; God is much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by laſie ſlugiſh Prayers.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> Thoſe are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved that have evil ends in their praying. <hi>Ye ask, and receive not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe ye ask amiſſe, that ye may conſume it upon your luſts.</hi> When a mans ends in Prayer are bad, his Prayer cannot be good.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> thoſe are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, that pray for light and ſlight things: As for example, when men are at play, to pray to God to win the game, or the like: Theſe kind of prayers are very diſpleaſing to God, and is a taking his Name in vain.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Fifthly.</note> Thoſe are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170392:67"/>that are Formal and Hypocritical in their Prayers, that pray without any delight in the work; that ſeek God by fits, and not in ſincerity. <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Hypocrite, ſaith, <hi>Will God hear his cry when trouble cometh upon him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 27.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Will he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light himſelf in the Almighty? Will he alwayes call upon God?</hi> No, he will not; For he that ſerves not God out of the love he bears to him, cannot delight in Gods ſervice, neither will he be conſtant therein. But the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, and meer Formaliſt, doe not ſerve God out of the love they bear to him; therefore they cannot delight in Gods ſervice, neither will they be conſtant therein; neither doth God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of them, or their Prayers.</p>
            <p>Sixthly,<note place="margin">Sixthly.</note> Thoſe are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, that Pray without judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170392:67"/>or underſtanding, or for things unlawful. A man may pray with good affections, and yet ſinne, becauſe he prayes not with judgement, he underſtands not what he prays for: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and I will pray with underſtanding alſo.</hi> I will underſtand and know what I pray for: And Chriſt blameth the mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> as children for asking ſhe knew not what.<note place="margin">Mat. 20.22.</note> O what a ſad thing is it, that any ſhould be ſo ſottiſhly ignorant, as to think they pray to God, when they are ſaying the Ten Commandements; yet I fear there are ſuch amongſt us; If there be, I pray let me ask you theſe two things:
<list>
                  <item>1. Whom do you pray to?</item>
                  <item>2. What do you pray for?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Whom do you pray to,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170392:68"/>when you ſay the Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements? If you ſay you pray to God, (as all our Prayers ought to be directed to him) then tell me; Is it not horrid Blaſphemy to ſay, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me, &amp;c?</hi> that thou ſhouldeſt ſpeak to God, and tell him what is contained in the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, thinking while thou art ſo doing thou art pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him. O what a ſad thing is this! For in the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements God ſpeaks to us, and therein teaches us our duties to him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Tell me, what doe you pray for in the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements? can you tell me? ſurely no: For all our requeſts we make to God, are reduced by the Apoſtle to theſe four Heads:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1</note> 
               <hi>Supplications, Prayers, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſsions, and giving of Thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170392:68"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Supplications,</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of Evils.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Prayer,</hi> for the obtaining of good things.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Interceſsion,</hi> in the behalf of others.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> for benefits received.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now tell me, if any of you can apply any one of theſe to any of the Commandements: If not, then learn to underſtand them, and teach them to your children, that you, and they may know your duties to God and your Neighbour; but uſe them not as Prayers. For in Prayer we ſpeak to God; in the Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments God ſpeaks to us: And thoſe that uſe the Creed as a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er deſerve alſo to be reproved; the Arguments before uſed may be ſufficient to prove they pray without judgement. An other
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170392:69"/>ſort that pray without judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are thoſe that pray for unlawful things: as thoſe who would have fire from Heaven to deſtroy their enemies; but ſaith Chriſt to them,<note place="margin">Luke 9 54</note> 
               <hi>You know not of what ſpirit you are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, Thoſe are to be reproved, that pray, but yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to go on in their ſinnes. Gods ſervice is pretended, but the Devils work is performed by them. You that regard not Gods Lawes and Commands, but are lewd and ungodly, cruel and unmerciful; do you think God will hear your voice, when you will not hearken to his voice?<note place="margin">Prov. 28.9</note> 
               <hi>He that turns away his ear from hearing the Law, even his Prayers ſhall be an abomination.</hi> It is juſt with God,<note place="margin">Prov. 1.24, &amp;c.</note> that when we refuſe to hear him, he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to hear us. Saith <hi>David, If
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170392:69"/>I regard iniquity in my heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.18</note> 
               <hi>the Lord will not hear me.</hi> If thy heart incline to ſinne, Gods ear will not incline to thy Prayer. If thou ſinneſt with delight, God will not delight in thee, nor in thy Prayers.<note place="margin">Jer. 14.10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord unto this people, thus have they loved to wander, they have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained their feet, therefore the Lord doth not accept them,</hi> (and it follows) <hi>pray not for this people for their good; when they faſt, I will not hear their cry.</hi> You ſee that thoſe that delight in ſinne, God will neither hear their Prayers for themſelves, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for them. Saith the Lord, <hi>Pray not thou for this people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 7.16.</note> 
               <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lift up a cry nor prayer for them, neither make interceſsion to me, for I will not hear thee.</hi> And alſo, if thou beeſt unmerciful to others, God will not hear thy
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170392:70"/>Prayers, nor ſhew mercy unto thee:<note place="margin">Prov. 21.13.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſo ſtoppeth his ear at the cry of the poor, he ſhall alſo cry himſelf, but ſhall not be heard. He ſhall have judgement without mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>that hath ſhewed no mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly and laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> All thoſe deſerve to be reproved, that pray without Faith and fervency. He that prays doubtingly,<note place="margin">Jam. 1.6, 7</note> prays ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and ſhall get nothing by praying. He that hath not Faith in God, can never prevail with God in Prayer:<note place="margin">Mark 11.22, 23, 24.</note> For Faith is the condition upon which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of anſwer of prayers is made. To which alſo muſt be added Fervency:<note place="margin">Jam. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much.</hi> And therefore thoſe that have neither Faith, nor Fervency in their prayers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be reprehended: So much for this Uſe.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170392:70"/>
            <p>I come now to the third Uſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Uſe. Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</note> and that is for Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And that for all thoſe that are faithful and fervent, conſtant and frequent in this duty of Prayer: That pray e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day in their Family, or in ſecret, or both in their Family or ſecretly. For your Comfort go along with me, in theſe eight or nine things following.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, There is no Family where Prayer is conſtantly uſed Morning and Evening, but God uſually bleſſeth thoſe Families. As God bleſſed the houſe of <hi>Obed Edom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.11.</note> becauſe the Ark was in his houſe: So God bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thoſe Families where prayers are daily uſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, There are no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret prayers made unto God, but ſhall be anſwered: Saith Chriſt, <hi>When thou Prayeſt, enter into thy
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170392:71"/>cloſet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>and when thou haſt ſhut thy door, pray to thy Father which is in ſecret, and thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which ſeeth in ſecret, ſhall reward thee openly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, If thou canſt pray in Faith, it is a certain ſigne thou haft the truth of Grace; thou art a child of God, and ſhalt be ſaved.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. It is a ſigne of the truth of grace. Saith the Lord, <hi>I will pour upon them the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 12.10.</note> He that hath the ſpirit of Supplication, hath the ſpirit of Grace firſt, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he could not have the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Supplication.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. It is a ſigne thou art a child of God. Saith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe ye are ſonnes, God hath ſent forth the ſpirit of his Sonne into your hearts, crying Abba, Father.</hi> If thou wert not
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170392:71"/>a ſonne, thou couldeſt not call upon God as a Father.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. It is a certain ſigne thou ſhalt be ſaved.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>For whoſoever ſhall call upon the Name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved.</hi> He that by Faith calls upon God may miſſe of the particular mercy he begs for here; but he may be aſſured he ſhall not miſſe Eternal Salvation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: For the ſpirit of Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is a certain ſigne of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. If thy heart be ſincere in thy Prayers to God, God will accept of thee, although thou haſt many failings. <hi>For if there be firſt a willing minde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.</hi> God accepts not of our ſervice according to the worthineſſe of the work, but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170392:72"/>the willingneſſe of the mind in the work. So as he that unfainedly prays for, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſires Faith, Repentance, and other graces, he hath theſe graces in Gods eſteem, becauſe God accepts of the will for the deed.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. If thou, in the want of ability to utter words to God as thou deſireſt, canſt weep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and ſobbe out thy complaints with ſighs and groanes; Theſe thy deſires is a certain ſigne thou haſt the ſpirit of Prayer; for theſe ſighes and groanes could not be in thy prayers to God, but from the Spirit of God help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy infirmities in the duty; as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit helpeth our infirmities; for we know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought, but the ſpirit
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170392:72"/>it ſelf maketh interceſsion for us, with greanings which cannot be uttered.</hi> Theſe unutterable groanes proceed from the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural motion of Gods Spirit in thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, If thou canſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely ſeek God by Prayer, thou maieſt have comfort in all afflictions and trials that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal thee. You ſhall find <hi>David</hi> complaining of the unkind dealing of his Adverſaries, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 109. but ſaith he <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>I give my ſelf unto Prayer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 109.4</note> As if he ſhould have ſaid, I uſe no unlawful meanes againſt them, but my onely refuge and defence is prayer unto God. So did <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 16.20.</note> 
               <hi>My friends ſcorne me, but mine eyes poureth out tears unto God.</hi> I weep in my prayers, and wait upon God to right my caſe. And
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170392:73"/>doubtleſſe thoſe that accuſtome themſelves to a conſtant courſe of ſeeking God, ſhall have cauſe to rejoyce and magnifie God in the greateſt trials that can befal them: according to that prophetical prayer of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 40.16</note> 
               <hi>Let all thoſe that ſeek thee rejoyce, and be glad in thee; let ſuch as love thy ſalvation, ſay continually, the Lord be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, If thou keepeſt thy heart in a conſtant courſe of praying unto God: It is a certain ſigne, that the ſinne or judgement thou prayeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, ſhall be removed; or the mercy thou prayeſt for ſhall be granted.<note place="margin">Exod. 17.11.</note> While <hi>Moſes</hi> held up his hands in Prayer, <hi>Iſrael</hi> prevailed. There was no fear of enemies Conquering while <hi>Moſes</hi> was praying. And you
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170392:73"/>ſhall find <hi>Moſes</hi> devotion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Gods indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his people, <hi>Exodus</hi> 32.10 to 15 verſe, ſaith the Lord to <hi>Moſes, Let me alone, that my wrath may wax hot againſt them, and that I may conſume them:</hi> But <hi>Moſes</hi> would not let God alone, but continued praying for them: His Prayers are anſwered, the Judgement is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, Verſe 14.<note place="margin">Exod. 32, 14.</note> 
               <hi>And the Lord repented him of the evil which he thought to doe unto his people.</hi> And <hi>Jacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.26, 29.</note> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued wreſtling for a bleſſing, obtained it. If Prayer be not ſlackned, mercy ſhall be ſpeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If thou continueſt in a conſtant courſe of praying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, for grace, and for the removal of judgements or afflictions: know for thy comfort, thy ſinnes ſhall be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170392:74"/>pardoned, grace ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, and the judgements or afflictions ſhall be removed from thee, or ſanctified to thee for thy good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eightly, It is certain, That that God that calleth thee to the duty of Prayer, he is able, ready, and willing to hear and help thee. When <hi>Bartimeus</hi> went to Chriſt for his eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, and it was told him, <hi>Be of good comfort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 10.49.</note> 
               <hi>ariſe, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thee:</hi> Out of all queſtion, at this report, the heart of <hi>Bartimeus</hi> leapt within him; and he was confident, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt called him, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to grant his requeſt in reſtoring his ſight. So belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you may be confident, that God that calls you to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Prayer, he intends to hear, and anſwer you: For
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170392:74"/>he is able to help you:<note place="margin">Pſa. 115.3</note> 
               <hi>Our God is in Heaven, and he doth whoſoever he pleaſeth.</hi> And he is willing to help and comfort you, For <hi>like as a Father pittieth his children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſo the Lord pittieth them that fear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninethly and laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> All the Prayers of Gods faithful ſervants on earth, ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be heard and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in Heaven. This is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes true, with theſe three Cautions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, That thou beeſt a Righteous perſon, that doth the will of God:<note place="margin">Jam. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>The Prayer of the Righteous availeth much.</hi> Saith Chriſt,<note place="margin">Joh. 15.7.</note> 
               <hi>If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ye ſhall ask what ye will, and it ſhall be done unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170392:75"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, If ye ask in the Name of Chriſt: For, ſo ſaith Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn 16.23.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall ask the Father in my Name, he ſhall give it you</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, If your Prayers be according to the will of God. Saith the Apoſtle, <hi>This is the confidence that we have in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>that if we ask any thing according to his will, he heareth us.</hi> Onely know this, That although the Prayers of Gods ſervants ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; yet it may be not preſently. You muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Mercies you pray for, when you will; no, but ye muſt wait Gods time, which is the beſt time. Saith the Prophet,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.16.</note> 
               <hi>He that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, maketh not haſte.</hi> He is content to ſtay himſelf upon God, and wait his leaſure.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170392:75"/>So did <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 40.1.</note> 
               <hi>I waited pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently upon the Lord, and he enclined unto me, and heard my cry.</hi> And ſo did the Church, in <hi>Iſaiah, I will wait upon the Lord, that hideth his face from the houſe of</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <hi>and I will look for him.</hi> I ſhall conclude this Uſe with that in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30.18.<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.18.</note> And therefore will the Lord wait, that he may be gracious to you; and therefore will he be exalted, that he may have mercy upon you; for the Lord is a God of judgement, Bleſſed are all they that wait for him. So much for the third Uſe, which hath been for Conſolation.</p>
            <p>I come now to the fourth and laſt Uſe,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Uſe.</hi> Laſtly.</note> which is for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo,<note place="margin">Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> that it is the Duty
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170392:76"/>of all the people of God to Pray: Then I beſeech you be exhorted to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Duty. In the proſecution of this Uſe I ſhall,</p>
            <p>Firſt, give you divers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in the Duty of Prayer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall anſwer two material Queſtions concerning Prayer.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and laſtly, I ſhall lay down ſome Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the Duty of Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <note place="margin">Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Prayer.</note> of the firſt; I ſhall lay down nine or tenne Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the duty of Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Labour to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to Chriſt, that your perſon may be accepted, and you may be in favour with God. Till this be done, your Prayers will not be anſwered. God accepted of <hi>Abel</hi> firſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.4.</note>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170392:76"/>then he accepted of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. His Faith in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Meſſiah was that which made both his perſon and Sacrifice accepted with God.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.4.</note> So by Faith get an intereſt in Chriſt, and then both thy perſon and thy Prayers ſhall be accepted.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, For the matter of your Prayers, be ſure they be for ſuch things as are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Gods will. Thou haſt no warrant to ask what God hath not promiſed to give: For this purpoſe it is requiſite, you ſhould be well verſed in the Scriptures: And then turn the Promiſes into Prayers; ſo ſhall you ſpeak to God in his own language, your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts ſhall be according to his will,<note place="margin">1 John 5.14.</note> and then you may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident you ſhall be heard.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170392:77"/>
            <p>Thirdly, Approach to God in Prayer, with a contrite and broken heart for ſinne: As God will not deſpiſe a contrite and broken heart;<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17</note> ſo neither will he deſpiſe the Prayers that proceed from ſuch a heart. When the heart is broken for ſinne, God will alſo break that heart from ſinne, and ſatisfie the deſires of that ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Take heed of wandring thoughts in Prayer: and let thy heart and thy tongue goe alwayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Wandring thoughts (or vaine thoughts) are bad at any time, worſt of all in Prayer. God complaines of them,<note place="margin">Jer. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>How long ſhall vaine thoughts lodge within thee.</hi> Doe thou complain
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170392:77"/>of them to God. And ſeek not that with thy tongue, which thy heart doth not deſire; for if thou doſt, God ſeeth thy hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrſie, and will hate thee for it:<note place="margin">Heb. 4.13.</note> For <hi>all things are naked and open unto the eyes of him with whom we have to doe</hi> (in Prayer.)</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Take a Catalogue of (and bear in minde) all the ſinnes thou art to pray againſt, and all the graces thou art to pray for. Mind alſo the mercies and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings thou art to pray for. And think alſo of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and bleſſings thou haſt received, to be thankfull for them. The ſerious thoughts and meditations of theſe things, will furniſh thee
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170392:78"/>with ſufficient matter for Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, in all thy Prayers, have a high eſteem of God. Saith <hi>Soloman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.2</note> 
               <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be haſty to utter any thing before God; for God is in Heaven, and thou upon Earth, therefore let thy words be few.</hi> Think ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what a God it is thou ſpeakeſt to; theſe thoughts will make thee reverent, and ſerious in the duty.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, In all your Prayers to God, be as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be thankful to God for what you have received, as to ſeek him for what you want. I fear it is a ſinne too common amongſt Gods children, to be ſo mindful of what they want, as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170392:78"/>to be thankful for what they have. But take heed of this; the way to obtain new mercies, is to be thankful for the old. Saith <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits towards me? I will take the cup of ſalvation, and call upon the Name of the Lord.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, I will be thankful to God for what I have, and I will call upon him for more bleſſings.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eighthly, When you have ended your Prayers, Take heed you reſt not in the Duty, but mourn for the ſinnes of the Duty; and look up to God for an Anſwer: So did <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>In the morning I will direct my Prayer unto thee, and I will look up.</hi> He doth not reſt in the duty done,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170392:79"/>but continued praying, and looking up to God for an anſwer: So doe you take heed, you reſt not in the duty, neither let the work be tedious to you: For as painfulneſſe of ſpeaking ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth a ſick body, ſo doth irkſomneſſe in praying a ſick ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Ninethly, Let Gods glory be your utmoſt aime in all your Prayers. Seek not your ſelves, nor your own ends in your Supplications, but the glory of God onely. Saith Chriſt,<note place="margin">John 8.50</note> 
               <hi>I ſeek not my own glory.</hi> Neither ſhould we ſeek our own glory in any thing we doe, much leſſe in Prayer: For if Gods glory be not our ends and aimes in Prayer, it will render our prayers odious unto God.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170392:79"/>
            <p>Tenthly, and laſtly,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> Take heed of a ſelviſh ſpirit in Prayer. Pray not onely for your ſelves and your Friends; but (as the Apoſtle exhorts) <hi>for all men,</hi> of all degrees,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1, 2.</note> Magiſtrates and Miniſters, &amp;c. Pray not onely for your friends that pleaſure you, but alſo for your enemies that deſpitefully uſe you, as our Saviour exhorts.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> The more publick our ſpirits are in the duty of Prayer, the more pleaſing are our Prayers unto God. It is good to have a publick ſpirit in private duties. Take heed therefore of a ſelviſh or private ſpirit in the duty of Prayer. Thus by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation I have given you divers directions in the duty of Prayer; obſerve them for your good.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
            <p>I come now in the ſecond
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170392:80"/>place, to Anſwer two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Queſtions concerning Prayer.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this;<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Quest.</note> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell how to pray, I want utterance: Whether or no is not my reading a Form of Prayer acceptable with God in this caſe?</p>
            <p>It is farre better to uſe the help of a good Prayer Book,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> then not to pray at all: onely be ſure, that the Prayers you read be ſutable to your condition. And take heed the ſpirit of Grace and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation be not wanting in him that reads the Prayer, nor in them that hear it. The beſt Reformed Churches hath, and doth read Set-formes of Prayer.</p>
            <p>It is Objected,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> To read a Sermon, is not to Preach;
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170392:80"/>therefore to read a Prayer is not to Pray.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> the reaſon is not alike in both; For the gift of Preaching is not ſhewed in reading, therefore reading a Sermon is not preaching: but the grace and gift of Prayer may be ſhewed in reading of a Prayer.</p>
            <p>Again it is Objected,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> If we read Formes of Prayer, then we ſtinct the Spirit.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer no.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> For if we joyn with another that prayes without a Form, his prayer is a Form to us: For although our hearts be more enlarged, yet we muſt ſtick cloſe to the words of him with whom we joyn in Prayer. So as this is no ſtinting of the ſpirit: For when thou art alone, thou maiſt enlarge thy ſelf. Yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170392:81"/>know, that the enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the heart ſtands not ſo much in the multitude and variety of expreſſions, as in the extent of the affections. So that although you be tyed up in words, yet there is no tie upon the affections; they may be enlarged in putting up the ſame petition, when an other is ſtraightned. Thus you ſee a man may read and uſe Formes of Prayer: onely take theſe two Cautions:</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Take heed you do not reſt in this way: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though reading is a help to Prayer; yet muſt you labour to pray without it. A child that cannot goe alone may be helpt to go, but ye muſt not be alwayes children; not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes doe thus.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Take heed you
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170392:81"/>neglect not to uſe and exerciſe the grace God have given you. For know this, there is no man, that hath any work of Grace upon his heart, but is, able to pray without reading, or uſing a Set-forme of Prayer. There was never any man in extreme need, but he could tell how to expreſſe his wants to thoſe that could relieve him without reading them.</p>
            <p>I come to anſwer the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Queſtion; which is this;<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Quest.</note> I cannot read, and I know not how to pray; What ſhall I do in this caſe?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> Go to God with <hi>David,</hi> and ſay, <hi>O Lord, open thou my lips,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.15</note> 
               <hi>and my mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy praiſe.</hi> Put into my mouth what I ſhall ſpeak unto thee. And then doubtleſſe, that God that bids his
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170392:82"/>people take unto them words,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.2.</note> and hath promiſed his ſpirit ſhall help their infirmities,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26</note> will undoubtedly give them words to ſeek him with. For God never puts a man upon a duty, but he will help him in it. As you may ſee in the example of <hi>Moſes;</hi> he complaines of his inability to ſpeak; God bids him go, and promiſeth to be with his mouth,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.10, 11, 12.</note> and to teach him what he ſhall ſay. And <hi>Moſes</hi> (by Gods help) was migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in words (as well) as in deeds.<note place="margin">Acts 7.22.</note> Let a man be never ſo full of words and matter, he cannot bring it forth in Prayer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods aſſiſtance; he cannot utter his own conceptions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods help.<note place="margin">Prov. 16.1</note> Saith <hi>Solomon, The preparation of the heart in man, and the anſwer of the tongue is from the Lord.</hi> A
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170392:82"/>man can neither prepare his heart to ſpeak, nor ſpeak what he hath prepared, without Gods aſſiſtance. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore go to God to give thee a heart, and words to ſpeak to him with; and doubtleſſe, that God that hath promiſed to give a mouth to his children,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.19. Luk. 21.15.</note> to ſpeak before their enemies, He will not deny to give them words, when they come by Prayer to ſpeak before him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. For a full anſwer to this queſtion, take theſe two Concluſions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, God never gives a man an heart to pray,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.17</note> but he lends an ear to hear.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, He that hath an heart to pray, will ſeek God to give him words; And he that with a ſincere heart ſeeks God to give him words, ſhall never
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170392:83"/>want words to ſeek him with. Haſt thou then a heart? go to God, and he will give thee words;<note place="margin">Pſa. 19.14</note> Pray with <hi>David, Let the words of my mouth, and the meditations of my heart, be acceptable in thy ſight O Lord my ſtrength and my redeemer:</hi> And then God will make thy words acceptable in his ſight. For there is no mouth into which God cannot put fit words to ſeek him with. When God puts forth his power, the weakeſt inſtrument ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to do his will. As ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared,<note place="margin">Num. 22.27, to 32 verſe.</note> when God enabled <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> Aſſe to convince his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And ſo much for the Anſwer to the two Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I come now in the third and laſt place to lay down ſome encouragements to the Duty
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170392:83"/>of Prayer: I have already given divers in the uſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. To all which, in the cloſe, let me adde theſe three or four following.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag.</note> God is ſo well pleaſed with Prayer, that he hath heard the Prayers of men for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral things that had no grace. You may ſee this in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of King <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 21.24, to the end.</note> who ſold himſelf to work wickedneſſe in the ſight of God; Yet when he heard the judgement threatned againſt him, he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf by Faſting and Prayer; and although it was not the humiliation of a true Penitent; for he turned not from his ſinnes: yet ſee what God ſaith to the Prophet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him;<note place="margin">1 King. 21.29.</note> 
               <hi>Seeſt thou how</hi> A hab <hi>bumbles himſelf before me? I will not bring the evil in his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170392:84"/>dayes, but in his ſonnes dayes will I bring the evil upon his houſe.</hi> If God be thus moved with the humiliation and prayer of a wicked man, as to put off, or deferre a temporal judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: how can God deny the Prayers of thoſe that have the truth of grace, when they ſeek him for pardon of ſinne, and ſpiritual bleſſings? If exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal humiliation prevail thus with God, O how prevalent are the Prayers of tender bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-hearted ſinners,<note place="margin">2 King. 22.19.</note> ſuch as good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> was?</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag.</note> There is no man that hath ſet upon this duty of Prayer with a ſincere heart, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to go on in the practice thereof, although he hath been never ſo weak and unable to the work at the firſt, yet in time he hath found God car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170392:84"/>of him on in it beyond expectations, and hath found a daily growth and increaſe of Grace and abilities to Pray: <hi>God deſpiſeth not the day of ſmall things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 4.10.</note> Though grace in the ſoul of him that humbly ſeeks God. be at the firſt but as a grain of Muſtard ſeed:<note place="margin">Mat. 13.1 31.</note> yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward it ſhall abundantly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, according to that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,<note place="margin">Job 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>Though thy beginning was ſmall, yet thy latter end ſhall greatly encreaſe.</hi> And that of our Saviour,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.29.</note> 
               <hi>For unto every one that hath ſhall be given, and he ſhall have abundance:</hi> He that faithfully improves that little grace he hath, in an humble conſtant ſeeking of God for more grace, he ſhall have <hi>grace for grace,</hi> or grace upon grace;<note place="margin">John 1.16.</note> one grace after another, a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encreaſe of grace, until he
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170392:85"/>hath abundance of grace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag.</note> God is more ready to anſwer his people then they are to ask; more forward to grant, then they are to crave. For if any with an upright heart reſolve to ſeek God, and in their hearts are ſtudying how to ſeek him, God will hear them before they pray, and will anſwer them when they pray; according to that promiſe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 65.24.</note> 
               <hi>Before they call I will anſwer, and whiles they are yet ſpeaking I will hear.</hi> Our Heavenly Father knoweth what things we have need of before we ask him:<note place="margin">Mat. 6.8.</note> And therefore before we call, while we are yet thinking to ſpeak, he will hear and anſwer us, by giving us aſſiſtance in ſpeaking to him, ſo as while we are ſpeaking, he will alſo hear and anſwer us;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170392:85"/>according to that promiſe alſo in <hi>Iſaiah, Then ſhalt thou call,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58.9.</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord will anſwer; thou ſhalt cry, and he ſhall ſay here I am.</hi> Upon thy cry, he will readily hear and help thee:<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.1.</note> For <hi>he is a very preſent help in time of trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement I ſhall mention,<note place="margin">Laſtly.</note> is this: God is ſo well pleaſed with Prayer, as that he maketh his readineſſe to hear his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Prayers, and to pardon their ſinnes upon humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement thereof, a ground of Encouragement to quicken them to the duty. Saith <hi>David, I acknowledge my ſinne unto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>and mine iniquity have I not hid; I ſaid I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my tranſgreſsions unto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of my ſinne: For this ſhall
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170392:86"/>every one that is godly pray unto thee in a time when thou maieſt be found.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, becauſe thou haſt been ſo merciful to me, in hearing my Prayer, and pardoning my ſin; therefore ſhall every godly man be encouraged to pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for the like mercy. What an encouragement is this to Prayer, when we hear that every one that went to God, humbly acknowledging their ſinnes,<note place="margin">Prov. 28.13.</note> obtained mercy accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Promiſe, <hi>Whoſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth and forſaketh his ſinnes, ſhall have mercy.</hi> And that of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>If we confeſſe our ſinnes, he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſinnes, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſſe.</hi> For this ſhall every one that is godly pray unto God in a time when he may be found. This ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170392:86"/>(of God ſo readily hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others) will undoubted be an Encouragement to every godly man to pray unto God. But as for wicked and ungodly men, neither this, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther argument I have uſed in all my ſeveral Sermons on this ſubject, will in the leaſt move them to the performance of this duty of Prayer.</p>
            <p>I have ſhewed you what Prayer is: The ſeveral kindes of Prayer: The Preparations to Prayer: The Duties in Prayer: The Geſtures of Prayer: The Motives to Prayer: The Times of Prayer: And I have anſwered divers Objections about Prayer. I have alſo gone through the ſeveral Uſes, of Information, Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, Conſolation, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation: In all which I have uſed my uttermoſt endeavour, to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170392:87"/>perſwade you to this ſo neceſſary a duty. And ſhall all my labour be in vain? I hope better things of you, and ſuch as accompany Salvation. Wherefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, for the Lords ſake. For the Churches ſake: For your own Souls ſake, Pray. You that have not heretofore prayed, Pray: You that have formerly prayed, pray more. That which was the concluſion of a godly Martyrs Letters,<note place="margin">John Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</note> ſhall be the Concluſion of my Sermon, and this ſubject, Pray, pray, pray.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
